<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-30T20:11:59+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fulcria Labs Blog</title><subtitle>Golf tech insights, swing analysis tips, and AI-powered improvement</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to Fix a Golf Hook: 7 Proven Drills and Fixes</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-golf-hook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Fix a Golf Hook: 7 Proven Drills and Fixes" /><published>2026-01-30T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-golf-hook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-golf-hook/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-to-fix-a-golf-hook-7-proven-drills-and-fixes">How to Fix a Golf Hook: 7 Proven Drills and Fixes</h1>

<p>A hook might feel better off the clubface than a slice—at least you’re hitting it solid—but a ball that starts right and dives left into the trees is just as costly as one that slices the other way.</p>

<p>The frustrating part? Many golfers develop a hook <em>after</em> they’ve fixed their slice, turning one problem into another. Let’s break down why hooks happen and how to straighten them out.</p>

<h2 id="what-causes-a-golf-hook">What Causes a Golf Hook?</h2>

<p>A hook happens when the clubface is closed relative to your swing path at impact. Unlike a slice (open face + out-to-in path), a hook combines:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Clubface significantly closed</strong> to the target line</li>
  <li><strong>Swing path from inside</strong> (which is actually good—you just need to match face to path)</li>
</ul>

<p>The ball starts right of your target (for right-handed golfers), then curves sharply left. The more closed the face relative to path, the more severe the curve.</p>

<h3 id="hook-vs-draw-vs-snap-hook">Hook vs. Draw vs. Snap Hook</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Draw</strong>: Slight right-to-left movement, lands near target</li>
  <li><strong>Hook</strong>: Excessive curve, misses left of target</li>
  <li><strong>Snap Hook / Duck Hook</strong>: Severe, low curve that dives quickly—often from an extremely closed face</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-7-most-common-hook-causes">The 7 Most Common Hook Causes</h2>

<h3 id="1-grip-too-strong">1. Grip Too Strong</h3>

<p>The most frequent hook cause. When both hands rotate too far clockwise on the grip (for right-handers), the face naturally closes through impact.</p>

<p><strong>Check yourself</strong>: Look down at your grip. If you can see 3-4 knuckles on your left hand, your grip is too strong.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Rotate both hands slightly counterclockwise until you see only 2 knuckles on your left hand. This feels weak at first but allows the face to stay more square.</p>

<h3 id="2-clubface-closed-at-address">2. Clubface Closed at Address</h3>

<p>If you set up with the clubface already closed, you’re pre-programming a hook before you even swing.</p>

<p><strong>Check yourself</strong>: At address, the leading edge should be perpendicular to your target line, not aimed left.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Use alignment sticks in practice. Set one for your target line and consciously square the face to it.</p>

<h3 id="3-overactive-hands-through-impact">3. Overactive Hands Through Impact</h3>

<p>Rolling your hands over too aggressively through the hitting zone closes the face rapidly. This often comes from the old advice to “release” the club, taken too far.</p>

<p><strong>Check yourself</strong>: In slow-motion video, watch if your forearms rotate excessively through impact.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Practice the “logo up” drill—keep the logo on your glove facing the sky longer through impact.</p>

<h3 id="4-body-stalling-hands-flipping">4. Body Stalling, Hands Flipping</h3>

<p>When your body rotation stops, your hands take over. Active hands without body rotation = rapid face closure.</p>

<p><strong>Check yourself</strong>: At the finish, is your belt buckle facing the target? If not, you stalled.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Focus on continuous rotation through the ball. Feel like your chest beats your hands to the finish.</p>

<h3 id="5-ball-position-too-far-back">5. Ball Position Too Far Back</h3>

<p>A ball positioned too far back in your stance forces you to catch it earlier in the swing arc—when the face is still closing.</p>

<p><strong>Check yourself</strong>: For driver, ball should be just inside your lead heel. For irons, progressively more centered.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Use a ball position check in every practice session. <a href="/blog/golf-ball-position-guide/">Read our ball position guide</a> for proper placement with each club.</p>

<h3 id="6-swing-path-too-far-from-inside">6. Swing Path Too Far From Inside</h3>

<p>An exaggerated inside-out path isn’t bad by itself—it’s what creates a draw. But when the face doesn’t match, you get hooks.</p>

<p><strong>Check yourself</strong>: In video, does your club approach the ball from well inside? Do your divots point right?</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: You don’t necessarily need to change your path—just match your face to it better. A slightly more neutral path can also help.</p>

<h3 id="7-tension-in-forearms-and-hands">7. Tension in Forearms and Hands</h3>

<p>Grip pressure that’s too tight causes the forearms to activate, rotating the face closed.</p>

<p><strong>Check yourself</strong>: Rate your grip pressure 1-10. If it’s above 4-5, you’re probably too tight.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Lighten your grip, especially with the trail hand. Sam Snead’s famous advice: hold the club like you’re holding a small bird.</p>

<h2 id="7-drills-to-fix-your-hook">7 Drills to Fix Your Hook</h2>

<h3 id="drill-1-the-split-grip-drill">Drill 1: The Split-Grip Drill</h3>

<p>Separate your hands 2-3 inches apart on the grip and hit short shots. This prevents the hands from rolling over too quickly.</p>

<p><strong>How to do it</strong>:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Place your lead hand in normal position</li>
  <li>Drop your trail hand 2-3 inches lower</li>
  <li>Make 50-75% swings focusing on keeping the face stable</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="drill-2-glove-under-trail-arm">Drill 2: Glove Under Trail Arm</h3>

<p>Tuck a glove or headcover under your trail armpit. If it falls before impact, you’re getting “disconnected”—which leads to flippy hands.</p>

<p><strong>How to do it</strong>:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Tuck object under trail arm at address</li>
  <li>Make swings keeping it in place through impact</li>
  <li>Focus on body rotation rather than arm action</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="drill-3-alignment-stick-in-belt-loop">Drill 3: Alignment Stick in Belt Loop</h3>

<p>Thread an alignment stick through your lead-side belt loop, pointing at the target. Through impact, rotate until the stick points left of target.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works</strong>: Forces full body rotation, preventing the stall that causes hand flip.</p>

<h3 id="drill-4-trail-arm-only-swings">Drill 4: Trail Arm Only Swings</h3>

<p>Make slow-motion swings with just your trail hand. Focus on keeping the palm facing the sky longer through impact.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works</strong>: Trains the trail arm to extend rather than rotate, which squares (rather than closes) the face.</p>

<h3 id="drill-5-ball-position-check">Drill 5: Ball Position Check</h3>

<p>Place two alignment sticks on the ground—one for target line, one perpendicular for ball position. Hit shots from correct positions for each club.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works</strong>: Ensures you’re not positioning the ball too far back, which catches the face while it’s still closing.</p>

<h3 id="drill-6-the-pause-drill">Drill 6: The Pause Drill</h3>

<p>Make a normal backswing, pause 2 seconds at the top, then swing through. This breaks the tension pattern that causes hooks.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works</strong>: Eliminates the quick, handsy transition that throws timing off.</p>

<h3 id="drill-7-aim-the-handle-drill">Drill 7: Aim the Handle Drill</h3>

<p>At impact, focus on the butt of the club pointing at your belt buckle, not behind you. This keeps the face from closing too quickly.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works</strong>: Maintains proper shaft angle through impact, preventing flip.</p>

<h2 id="common-mistakes-when-fixing-a-hook">Common Mistakes When Fixing a Hook</h2>

<h3 id="dont-weaken-your-grip-too-much">Don’t Weaken Your Grip Too Much</h3>

<p>Going from a strong grip to a weak grip often trades a hook for a slice. Make small adjustments—one knuckle at a time.</p>

<h3 id="dont-aim-right-to-compensate">Don’t Aim Right to Compensate</h3>

<p>Aiming right and playing the hook just grooves a bad pattern. Fix the cause instead of managing the symptom.</p>

<h3 id="dont-forget-the-cause-hierarchy">Don’t Forget the Cause Hierarchy</h3>

<p>Check grip first, then setup, then swing. Most hooks start in the grip—you might not need to change your swing at all.</p>

<h2 id="using-video-to-diagnose-your-hook">Using Video to Diagnose Your Hook</h2>

<p>Recording your swing reveals what you can’t feel:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Face-on view</strong>: Check ball position and hand rotation through impact</li>
  <li><strong>Down-the-line view</strong>: Check swing path and face angle at address</li>
  <li><strong>Slow motion</strong>: Watch forearm rotation through the hitting zone</li>
</ol>

<p><a href="/blog/phone-golf-swing-video/">Recording your swing with your phone</a> takes 30 seconds and shows exactly why you’re hooking.</p>

<h2 id="when-to-see-a-professional">When to See a Professional</h2>

<p>If you’ve tried these fixes for 3-4 practice sessions without improvement:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A lesson can identify your specific hook cause in minutes</li>
  <li>Equipment fitting might reveal ill-fitted clubs (lie angle, shaft flex)</li>
  <li>Custom fitting ensures your fixes aren’t fighting your equipment</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="/blog/golf-lesson-frequency/">When is it time for lessons?</a></p>

<h2 id="quick-reference-hook-fix-checklist">Quick Reference: Hook Fix Checklist</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Symptom</th>
      <th>Likely Cause</th>
      <th>First Fix</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Low, diving hook</td>
      <td>Extremely closed face</td>
      <td>Check grip strength</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>High hook</td>
      <td>Closed face + path issue</td>
      <td>Ball position + rotation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Hook with driver only</td>
      <td>Driver setup different</td>
      <td>Ball forward + tee height</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Hook with irons only</td>
      <td>Divots pointing right</td>
      <td>Match face to path</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Inconsistent hooks</td>
      <td>Grip pressure changes</td>
      <td>Lighter, consistent grip</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Hooks come from a clubface that’s closed relative to your swing path. Unlike slices, you already have the valuable inside-out path—you just need to match your face to it.</p>

<p>Start with the grip. More than half of hook problems are solved there. Then check ball position and setup before making swing changes. Small adjustments, made consistently, will straighten that hook into a controlled draw.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="/blog/fix-golf-slice/">How to Fix a Golf Slice</a> - The opposite problem, similar fixes</li>
  <li><a href="/blog/golf-grip-guide/">Golf Grip Guide: How to Hold the Club</a> - The #1 cause of hooks</li>
  <li><a href="/blog/golf-ball-position-guide/">Golf Ball Position Guide</a> - Proper positioning for every club</li>
  <li><a href="/blog/fix-over-the-top-golf-swing/">How to Fix Over-the-Top Golf Swing</a> - Common swing path issue</li>
  <li><a href="/blog/golf-club-face-control/">Club Face Control Guide</a> - Mastering face angle</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p><strong>Stop guessing why you hook—see it clearly.</strong>
<a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Swing Analyzer</a> shows your face angle and path at impact in 90 seconds. Upload a swing and see exactly what’s causing your curve.</p>]]></content><author><name>Fulcria Labs</name></author><category term="instruction" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stop hooking the ball with these 7 proven fixes. Learn why you hook, common causes, and drills that work for snap hooks and draws that won't stop curving.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Best Golf Swing Analyzer Apps for Android 2026 [Tested &amp;amp; Ranked]</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-android/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Best Golf Swing Analyzer Apps for Android 2026 [Tested &amp;amp; Ranked]" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-android</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-android/"><![CDATA[<p>Android users have excellent options for golf swing analysis - you just need to know which apps actually work on your device.</p>

<p>The good news? Modern Android flagships (Samsung Galaxy, Pixel, OnePlus) have incredible cameras with slow-motion capabilities up to 960fps. The question is: which app takes full advantage of that hardware?</p>

<p>We tested 7 golf swing analyzer apps on Android and ranked them for real-world use. Here’s what we found.</p>

<h2 id="quick-comparison-best-android-golf-swing-analyzers">Quick Comparison: Best Android Golf Swing Analyzers</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>App</th>
      <th>Best For</th>
      <th>Price</th>
      <th>AI Analysis</th>
      <th>Play Store Rating</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Swing Analyzer</strong></td>
      <td>Fast feedback</td>
      <td>Free tier</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>4.7</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>V1 Golf</strong></td>
      <td>Coach integration</td>
      <td>$99/yr</td>
      <td>Limited</td>
      <td>4.5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>18Birdies</strong></td>
      <td>GPS + swing combo</td>
      <td>$99/yr</td>
      <td>Basic</td>
      <td>4.4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>SWEE AI</strong></td>
      <td>Data nerds</td>
      <td>$150/yr</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>4.3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>GolfFix AI</strong></td>
      <td>Free option</td>
      <td>Free</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>4.5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Hudl Technique</strong></td>
      <td>Drawing tools</td>
      <td>Free</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>4.4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Golf Swing Analyzer</strong></td>
      <td>Budget option</td>
      <td>Free</td>
      <td>Basic</td>
      <td>4.2</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>Note: Sportsbox AI and Mustard Golf are iOS-only as of January 2026.</em></p>

<h2 id="our-top-3-picks-for-android">Our Top 3 Picks for Android</h2>

<h3 id="best-overall-swing-analyzer">Best Overall: Swing Analyzer</h3>

<p><strong>Why it wins:</strong> 90-second AI analysis on any Android phone. No waiting hours for feedback - you get results while you’re still at the range. Works without a tripod, which matters when you don’t want to haul extra gear.</p>

<p><strong>Key features:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Instant AI grading with letter grades (A-F)</li>
  <li>Handicap prediction that’s surprisingly accurate</li>
  <li>No tripod needed - works with phone propped up</li>
  <li>Clean interface that doesn’t require a tutorial</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Price:</strong> Free tier available, premium for advanced features</p>

<p><strong>Best for:</strong> Android users who want immediate, actionable feedback without complexity.</p>

<p><strong>Android note:</strong> Works smoothly on most devices running Android 10+. Optimized for Samsung Galaxy and Pixel cameras.</p>

<p><a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Try Swing Analyzer Free</a></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="best-for-coach-integration-v1-golf">Best for Coach Integration: V1 Golf</h3>

<p><strong>Why it’s great:</strong> The industry standard for lesson sharing. If your instructor uses V1 (most PGA pros do), this makes remote lessons seamless. The Android version has full feature parity with iOS.</p>

<p><strong>Key features:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Drawing tools for swing markup</li>
  <li>Split-screen comparison with tour pros</li>
  <li>Voice-over lesson recordings</li>
  <li>Shared libraries between student and coach</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Price:</strong> $99/year</p>

<p><strong>Best for:</strong> Golfers working with a teaching pro who want to share swings between sessions.</p>

<p><strong>Limitation:</strong> AI analysis is basic - it’s designed for human coaches to add value.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="best-free-option-golffix-ai">Best Free Option: GolfFix AI</h3>

<p><strong>Why it’s great:</strong> Korean-developed app with a genuinely useful free tier. Detects 45+ swing issues using AI and is used in 63 countries. For $0, the analysis quality is impressive.</p>

<p><strong>Key features:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Free AI swing analysis (not just a demo)</li>
  <li>Detailed issue detection (early extension, casting, sway, etc.)</li>
  <li>Before/after comparison tools</li>
  <li>Works on mid-range Android devices</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Price:</strong> Free (with optional premium upgrades)</p>

<p><strong>Best for:</strong> Budget-conscious golfers who want AI analysis without paying.</p>

<p><strong>Limitation:</strong> Interface isn’t as polished as premium options. Some features feel translated.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-rest-ranked">The Rest, Ranked</h2>

<h3 id="4-18birdies-99year">4. 18Birdies ($99/year)</h3>

<p>Primarily a GPS rangefinder and stat tracker that includes swing analysis. Good if you want one app for everything on the course. The swing analyzer isn’t as deep as dedicated options, but the all-in-one value is solid.</p>

<p><strong>Android note:</strong> Works well, though battery drain can be high with GPS running.</p>

<h3 id="5-swee-ai-150year">5. SWEE AI ($150/year)</h3>

<p>Detailed metrics and clean interface. Requires a tripod setup for best results, which adds friction. Android version works but some users report occasional sync issues.</p>

<p><strong>Android note:</strong> Performance varies by device. Works best on flagship phones.</p>

<h3 id="6-hudl-technique-free">6. Hudl Technique (Free)</h3>

<p>Originally built for coaches across multiple sports. Excellent drawing and annotation tools. No AI analysis - you’re doing the work yourself. But if you just want slow-mo video with markup, it’s free and capable.</p>

<p><strong>Android note:</strong> Reliable on most devices. Simple and lightweight.</p>

<h3 id="7-golf-swing-analyzer-free">7. Golf Swing Analyzer (Free)</h3>

<p>Basic but functional. Records your swing and lets you draw lines on it. No AI, limited features, but it works. Good entry point if you’ve never used a swing analyzer.</p>

<p><strong>Android note:</strong> Works on older Android devices where other apps struggle.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="android-specific-considerations">Android-Specific Considerations</h2>

<h3 id="camera-quality-matters">Camera Quality Matters</h3>

<p>Not all Android phones are equal. For best results:</p>

<p><strong>Excellent:</strong> Samsung Galaxy S24/S23, Pixel 8 Pro, OnePlus 12
<strong>Good:</strong> Most 2023-2024 flagships from major brands
<strong>Challenging:</strong> Budget phones with basic cameras</p>

<p>If your phone can shoot 240fps slow-motion (check your camera settings), you’ll get quality similar to iPhone. Many Samsung Galaxy phones can shoot at 960fps, which is actually superior.</p>

<h3 id="check-slow-mo-settings">Check Slow-Mo Settings</h3>

<p>Before blaming an app:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Open your camera app</li>
  <li>Switch to slow-motion mode</li>
  <li>Look for FPS settings (120, 240, 480, 960)</li>
  <li>Use at least 240fps for swing analysis</li>
</ol>

<p>Many golfers use their Android’s slow-mo at 120fps, which is too choppy for proper analysis.</p>

<h3 id="storage-space">Storage Space</h3>

<p>High-frame-rate videos eat storage fast. A 10-second swing at 240fps can be 100MB+. Make sure you have space, or the app will fail to save recordings.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="how-we-tested">How We Tested</h2>

<p>We recorded the same swing with each app on a Samsung Galaxy S24 Ultra:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Outdoor range, natural lighting</li>
  <li>240fps slow-motion mode</li>
  <li>Face-on and down-the-line angles</li>
  <li>Same 12-handicap golfer</li>
</ul>

<p>We evaluated:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Speed:</strong> How fast do you get feedback?</li>
  <li><strong>Accuracy:</strong> Do suggestions match what a pro would say?</li>
  <li><strong>Usability:</strong> Is the interface intuitive?</li>
  <li><strong>Value:</strong> Worth it for the average golfer?</li>
  <li><strong>Android stability:</strong> Crashes, bugs, device compatibility</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="what-android-apps-are-missing-ios-only">What Android Apps Are Missing (iOS-Only)</h2>

<p>Some popular options don’t have Android versions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Sportsbox AI</strong> ($780/yr) - 3D biomechanics, iOS-only</li>
  <li><strong>Mustard Golf</strong> ($150/yr) - Drill recommendations, iOS-only</li>
  <li><strong>OnForm</strong> ($50/yr) - Lesson platform, iOS-only</li>
</ul>

<p>If you need these specific features, iOS has an edge. But for most golfers, the Android options are more than sufficient.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions</h2>

<h3 id="which-android-phones-work-best-for-golf-swing-analysis">Which Android phones work best for golf swing analysis?</h3>

<p>Samsung Galaxy S-series and Google Pixel are the best-supported. Any flagship from 2022+ will work well. Mid-range phones work but may have slower processing.</p>

<h3 id="do-i-need-a-tripod">Do I need a tripod?</h3>

<p>Depends on the app. Swing Analyzer, V1 Golf, and 18Birdies work fine propped up or handheld. SWEE AI really needs a tripod for best results. See our guide on <a href="/blog/phone-golf-swing-video/">recording your swing without a tripod</a> for practical tips.</p>

<h3 id="why-do-some-apps-only-work-on-iphone">Why do some apps only work on iPhone?</h3>

<p>Apple’s standardized hardware makes AI development easier. Android has thousands of device variations, so some developers skip it. The apps that do support Android well have invested in cross-platform compatibility.</p>

<h3 id="can-i-use-the-default-camera-app">Can I use the default camera app?</h3>

<p>Yes! Your phone’s slow-mo camera works fine for self-review. But you won’t get AI analysis, drawing tools, or structured feedback. Apps add value on top of hardware.</p>

<h3 id="will-these-apps-drain-my-battery">Will these apps drain my battery?</h3>

<p>Yes - video processing is intensive. Expect 15-20% battery use per hour of active recording and analysis. Bring a charger to the range.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>For fast, practical feedback on Android: <strong>Swing Analyzer</strong></p>

<p>If you work with a coach: <strong>V1 Golf</strong></p>

<p>Best free option: <strong>GolfFix AI</strong></p>

<p>All-in-one with GPS/stats: <strong>18Birdies</strong></p>

<hr />

<p>Android users aren’t second-class citizens in golf tech. The best apps work great on your device - you just need to pick one that matches how you actually practice.</p>

<p>Start simple. See improvement. Then decide if you need more.</p>

<p><a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Try Swing Analyzer Free</a> - Works great on Android. Get instant AI feedback on your next range session.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-iphone/">Best Golf Swing Analyzer Apps for iPhone 2026</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/best-free-golf-swing-analyzer-apps/">Best Free Golf Swing Analyzer Apps 2026</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/how-ai-analyzes-golf-swing/">How AI Analyzes Golf Swings (The Technology Explained)</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/phone-golf-swing-video/">How to Record Your Golf Swing with Just Your Phone</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/v1-golf-vs-sportsbox-ai/">V1 Golf vs Sportsbox AI Comparison</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/golf-feedback-timing-science/">The Science of Feedback Timing in Golf</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Fulcria Labs</name></author><category term="golf-technology" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="swing-analyzer" /><category term="android-apps" /><category term="golf-apps" /><category term="app-reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Looking for the best golf swing analyzer app for your Android phone? We tested 7 top-rated apps and ranked them by features, accuracy, and value. Find your perfect match.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-android.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-android.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Best Golf Swing Analyzer Apps for iPhone 2026 [Tested &amp;amp; Ranked]</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-iphone/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Best Golf Swing Analyzer Apps for iPhone 2026 [Tested &amp;amp; Ranked]" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-iphone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-iphone/"><![CDATA[<p>Your iPhone is already the best golf swing analyzer you own. You just need the right app to unlock it.</p>

<p>With an iPhone’s 240fps slow-motion camera, gyroscope, and powerful processor, you have professional-grade video analysis hardware in your pocket. The question is: which app makes the best use of it?</p>

<p>We tested 8 top iPhone golf swing analyzer apps and ranked them based on real-world use. Here’s what we found.</p>

<h2 id="quick-comparison-best-iphone-golf-swing-analyzers">Quick Comparison: Best iPhone Golf Swing Analyzers</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>App</th>
      <th>Best For</th>
      <th>Price</th>
      <th>AI Analysis</th>
      <th>Rating</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Swing Analyzer</strong></td>
      <td>Fast feedback</td>
      <td>Free tier</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>4.8</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>V1 Golf</strong></td>
      <td>Coach integration</td>
      <td>$99/yr</td>
      <td>Limited</td>
      <td>4.7</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Sportsbox AI</strong></td>
      <td>3D biomechanics</td>
      <td>$780/yr</td>
      <td>Advanced</td>
      <td>4.5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>SWEE AI</strong></td>
      <td>Data nerds</td>
      <td>$150/yr</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>4.6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>18Birdies</strong></td>
      <td>GPS + swing combo</td>
      <td>$99/yr</td>
      <td>Basic</td>
      <td>4.6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Mustard Golf</strong></td>
      <td>Drills</td>
      <td>$150/yr</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>4.5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>GolfFix AI</strong></td>
      <td>Free option</td>
      <td>Free</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>4.4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>OnForm</strong></td>
      <td>Lesson sharing</td>
      <td>$50/yr</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>4.7</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="our-top-3-picks">Our Top 3 Picks</h2>

<h3 id="best-overall-swing-analyzer">Best Overall: Swing Analyzer</h3>

<p><strong>Why it wins:</strong> 90-second AI analysis means you get feedback while you’re still at the range. Most apps make you wait hours or days for a coach to review your swing. By then, you’ve forgotten what you were working on.</p>

<p><strong>Key features:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Instant AI grading with fun letter grades</li>
  <li>Handicap guessing feature (surprisingly accurate)</li>
  <li>No tripod required - works with phone in your bag</li>
  <li>Clean, fast interface</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Price:</strong> Free tier available, premium for advanced features</p>

<p><strong>Best for:</strong> Golfers who want immediate, actionable feedback without the complexity.</p>

<p><a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Try Swing Analyzer Free</a></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="best-for-coach-integration-v1-golf">Best for Coach Integration: V1 Golf</h3>

<p><strong>Why it’s great:</strong> If you’re working with a teaching pro, V1 Golf is the industry standard. Most PGA instructors already know how to use it, which makes remote lessons smooth.</p>

<p><strong>Key features:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Drawing tools for lesson markup</li>
  <li>Split-screen comparison with pros</li>
  <li>Voice-over lesson recordings</li>
  <li>Library of pro swings for reference</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Price:</strong> $99/year</p>

<p><strong>Best for:</strong> Golfers taking regular lessons who want to share swings with their instructor.</p>

<p><strong>Limitation:</strong> The AI analysis is basic - it’s really designed for human coaches to use.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="best-for-deep-analysis-sportsbox-ai">Best for Deep Analysis: Sportsbox AI</h3>

<p><strong>Why it’s great:</strong> True 3D motion capture from your iPhone. No markers, no special equipment. If you want biomechanical data that rivals what tour pros get, this is it.</p>

<p><strong>Key features:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>3D kinematic sequence visualization</li>
  <li>Precise angle measurements (hip turn, shoulder tilt, etc.)</li>
  <li>Tour player comparison overlays</li>
  <li>Data export for nerds who love spreadsheets</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Price:</strong> $780/year (or $95/month)</p>

<p><strong>Best for:</strong> Serious competitive golfers or instructors who want quantifiable data.</p>

<p><strong>Limitation:</strong> Steep learning curve. Requires tripod for best results. Expensive.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-rest-ranked">The Rest, Ranked</h2>

<h3 id="4-swee-ai-150year">4. SWEE AI ($150/year)</h3>

<p>Solid AI analysis with detailed metrics. The interface is clean and the data is good. Main downside: requires a tripod setup, which adds friction to casual range sessions. Some users report UX frustrations.</p>

<h3 id="5-18birdies-99year">5. 18Birdies ($99/year)</h3>

<p>Primarily a GPS and stat-tracking app that added swing analysis as a feature. Good if you want one app for everything, but the swing analysis isn’t as deep as dedicated analyzers.</p>

<h3 id="6-mustard-golf-150year">6. Mustard Golf ($150/year)</h3>

<p>Built around drill recommendations. The AI identifies issues and then prescribes specific drills to fix them. Great concept, but the drill library is limited compared to what a human coach would offer.</p>

<h3 id="7-golffix-ai-free">7. GolfFix AI (Free)</h3>

<p>Korean-developed app with a strong free tier. Detects 45+ swing issues and is used in 63 countries. The analysis is impressive for free, though the interface isn’t as polished as premium options.</p>

<h3 id="8-onform-50year">8. OnForm ($50/year)</h3>

<p>Not really an “analyzer” - it’s a video sharing platform for coaches and students. Great drawing tools and lesson organization. No AI analysis, but perfect for remote lessons if your coach uses it.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="how-we-tested">How We Tested</h2>

<p>We recorded the same swing with each app under identical conditions:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Outdoor range, natural lighting</li>
  <li>iPhone 15 Pro in 240fps slow-mo</li>
  <li>Face-on and down-the-line angles</li>
  <li>Same handicap-level golfer (12 index)</li>
</ul>

<p>We evaluated:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Speed:</strong> How fast do you get feedback?</li>
  <li><strong>Accuracy:</strong> Do the suggestions match what a pro would say?</li>
  <li><strong>Usability:</strong> Can you figure it out without reading a manual?</li>
  <li><strong>Value:</strong> Is it worth the price for the average golfer?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="what-to-look-for-in-a-golf-swing-analyzer-app">What to Look for in a Golf Swing Analyzer App</h2>

<h3 id="1-feedback-speed">1. Feedback Speed</h3>
<p>The best time to fix your swing is immediately after you hit a bad shot. If an app makes you wait hours or days for analysis, you lose the “feel” context that makes the feedback useful. <a href="/blog/golf-feedback-timing-science/">The science of feedback timing</a> explains why immediate feedback leads to faster improvement.</p>

<p><strong>Our take:</strong> Anything over 10 minutes is too slow for range use. Instant AI feedback wins.</p>

<h3 id="2-no-tripod-required">2. No Tripod Required</h3>
<p>Here’s the dirty secret of swing analyzers: many require a tripod for accurate results. That’s fine for a dedicated practice session, but it adds friction to casual range time.</p>

<p><strong>Our take:</strong> Apps that work with your phone propped in your bag or held by a friend are more practical.</p>

<h3 id="3-actionable-feedback">3. Actionable Feedback</h3>
<p>“Your hip turn is 42 degrees” is useless if you don’t know what to do about it. The best apps translate metrics into simple fixes.</p>

<p><strong>Our take:</strong> Letter grades and plain-English tips beat raw numbers for most golfers.</p>

<h3 id="4-price-transparency">4. Price Transparency</h3>
<p>Some apps advertise “free” but paywall all useful features. Others charge $50/month for features you’ll use twice.</p>

<p><strong>Our take:</strong> Free tiers should actually be useful. Premium should be worth it.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions</h2>

<h3 id="can-i-use-my-iphone-camera-without-an-app">Can I use my iPhone camera without an app?</h3>
<p>Yes! The built-in slow-motion camera (240fps) is excellent for self-review. But you won’t get AI analysis, drawing tools, or any structured feedback. An app adds value on top of the hardware.</p>

<h3 id="do-i-need-the-latest-iphone">Do I need the latest iPhone?</h3>
<p>Most apps work fine on iPhone 11 and newer. The better your camera, the better your results - but you don’t need the newest model.</p>

<h3 id="why-do-some-apps-require-a-tripod">Why do some apps require a tripod?</h3>
<p>Pose estimation AI works best with consistent camera angles. Some apps (like Sportsbox AI) rely heavily on 3D reconstruction, which needs stable footage. Others (like Swing Analyzer) are optimized to work without one.</p>

<h3 id="can-these-apps-replace-a-lesson">Can these apps replace a lesson?</h3>
<p>No. AI can spot obvious issues like <a href="/blog/golf-downswing-sequence/">early extension or casting</a>, but it can’t feel your <a href="/blog/golf-grip-guide/">grip pressure</a> or see the mental game issues. Use apps to supplement lessons, not replace them.</p>

<h3 id="which-app-do-instructors-prefer">Which app do instructors prefer?</h3>
<p>V1 Golf is the industry standard for coach-student sharing. Most PGA pros know it. For solo practice, instructors increasingly recommend AI-powered options for quick feedback.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>If you want fast, practical feedback without complexity: <strong>Swing Analyzer</strong></p>

<p>If you work with a coach: <strong>V1 Golf</strong></p>

<p>If you want deep biomechanical data: <strong>Sportsbox AI</strong></p>

<p>If you want one app for everything (GPS + stats + swing): <strong>18Birdies</strong></p>

<p>If you want free: <strong>GolfFix AI</strong> or <strong>Swing Analyzer’s free tier</strong></p>

<hr />

<p>The best golf swing analyzer is the one you’ll actually use. Fancy metrics mean nothing if the app is so complicated you abandon it after a week.</p>

<p>Start with something simple. See real improvement. Then decide if you need more.</p>

<p><a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Try Swing Analyzer Free</a> - Get instant AI feedback on your next range session.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="/blog/best-golf-swing-analyzer-apps-android/">Best Golf Swing Analyzer Apps for Android 2026</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/best-free-golf-swing-analyzer-apps/">Best Free Golf Swing Analyzer Apps 2026</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/v1-golf-vs-sportsbox-ai/">V1 Golf vs Sportsbox AI: Head-to-Head</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/swee-ai-vs-v1-golf/">SWEE AI vs V1 Golf Comparison</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/how-ai-analyzes-golf-swing/">How AI Analyzes Golf Swings (The Technology Explained)</a></li>
  <li><a href="/blog/phone-golf-swing-video/">How to Record Your Golf Swing with Just Your Phone</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Fulcria Labs</name></author><category term="golf-technology" /><category term="reviews" /><category term="swing-analyzer" /><category term="iphone-apps" /><category term="golf-apps" /><category term="app-reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Looking for the best golf swing analyzer app for your iPhone? We tested 8 top-rated apps and ranked them by features, accuracy, and value. Find your perfect match.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-swing-analyzer-iphone-apps.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-swing-analyzer-iphone-apps.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating Lag in Your Golf Swing: The Secret to Effortless Power</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/creating-lag-golf-swing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating Lag in Your Golf Swing: The Secret to Effortless Power" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/creating-lag-golf-swing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/creating-lag-golf-swing/"><![CDATA[<p>Watch any tour pro in slow motion and you’ll see it: that angle between the lead arm and club shaft is preserved deep into the downswing. The club looks like it’s “lagging” behind the hands. Then, right before impact, it releases with explosive speed.</p>

<p>That’s lag. And it’s why professional golfers hit the ball 50+ yards farther than most amateurs—without looking like they’re swinging harder.</p>

<h2 id="what-lag-actually-is">What Lag Actually Is</h2>

<p>Lag is the angle between your lead arm and the club shaft during the <a href="/2026/01/25/golf-downswing-sequence/">downswing</a>. At the top of a good backswing, this angle is roughly 90 degrees from proper wrist hinge. Maintaining that angle as you start down is what creates lag.</p>

<p>Here’s the key insight: lag isn’t something you create. It’s something you <em>preserve</em>.</p>

<p>During the backswing, your wrists naturally hinge as the club gets heavy. That creates the angle. The challenge is keeping that angle intact during the transition and early downswing, instead of losing it immediately.</p>

<p>When you maintain the angle, you store energy. When you release it at the right moment—just before impact—that stored energy transfers into the ball.</p>

<h2 id="why-amateur-golfers-lose-lag">Why Amateur Golfers Lose Lag</h2>

<p>The natural human instinct is to hit <em>at</em> the ball. When you see the ball and want to hit it hard, your body wants to throw the club at it immediately from the top.</p>

<p>This is called “casting” or “early release.” Instead of maintaining the wrist angle, you straighten your wrists right at the transition. The club releases too early, and all that stored energy dissipates before it reaches the ball.</p>

<p>Common causes of lost lag:</p>

<p><strong>1. Upper body starting first</strong></p>

<p>The proper <a href="/2026/01/25/golf-downswing-sequence/">downswing sequence</a> is ground-up: lower body, torso, arms, then club. When your shoulders or arms initiate the downswing, the club tends to throw out immediately.</p>

<p><strong>2. “Hitting” instead of “swinging”</strong></p>

<p>The harder you try to hit the ball, the more you cast. Lag is actually easier to maintain when you swing at 80% effort with good sequence than when you swing all-out with bad sequence.</p>

<p><strong>3. Grip pressure</strong></p>

<p>Squeezing the club too tight prevents proper wrist hinge and makes early release more likely. A lighter grip allows the wrists to stay loaded longer.</p>

<p><strong>4. No awareness</strong></p>

<p>Many golfers don’t realize they’re losing lag. They feel like they’re “swinging hard” and don’t understand why they can’t generate tour-like distance. <a href="/2026/01/19/how-ai-analyzes-golf-swings/">Video analysis</a> reveals the truth.</p>

<h2 id="the-feeling-of-good-lag">The Feeling of Good Lag</h2>

<p>Lag doesn’t feel like you’re actively holding an angle. It feels like the club is trailing behind your hands naturally as your body rotates toward the target.</p>

<p>Some useful feels:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pulling the grip end toward the ball.</strong> Instead of throwing the clubhead at the ball, focus on pulling the handle. The head follows.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Keeping your back to the target longer.</strong> This creates space for the club to drop into the slot instead of casting over the top.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Delayed hit.</strong> Feel like you’re not even thinking about the ball until your hands are past hip height in the downswing.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>None of these feels is literally what’s happening, but they create the right motion for most golfers.</p>

<h2 id="lag-and-impact-position">Lag and Impact Position</h2>

<p>Lag connects directly to <a href="/2026/01/26/golf-impact-position/">impact position</a>. When you maintain lag and release it at the right moment:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Your hands arrive ahead of the clubhead</li>
  <li>The shaft leans forward toward the target</li>
  <li>You compress the ball with descending contact</li>
  <li>The clubhead reaches maximum speed right at impact—not before it</li>
</ul>

<p>This is why lag produces both power and solid contact. The ball compresses against the face, and you get that satisfying “click” that means you hit it pure.</p>

<p>Golfers who cast lose both benefits. The club passes the hands before impact, the shaft leans backward, and contact becomes scoopy and thin.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-build-lag-drills-that-work">How to Build Lag: Drills That Work</h2>

<h3 id="1-the-pump-drill">1. The Pump Drill</h3>

<p>Start at the top of your backswing. Pump the club down to hip height while maintaining your wrist angle, then go back to the top. Do this three times, then hit the ball on the fourth pump.</p>

<p>This trains your body to sequence correctly: lower body first, arms and club following.</p>

<h3 id="2-the-pause-at-the-top">2. The Pause at the Top</h3>

<p>Make a full backswing, then pause for a full second at the top. Feel your lower body start the downswing while your arms and club are still at the top.</p>

<p>This exaggerates the sequence separation that creates lag naturally.</p>

<h3 id="3-half-speed-swings-with-full-finish">3. Half-Speed Swings with Full Finish</h3>

<p>Swing at 50% speed but focus on finishing in a full, balanced position. At half speed, you can feel the sequence better. Your hands should be well past hip height before you feel the club release.</p>

<p>Record these swings. You’ll see more lag at half speed than at full speed—that tells you what to work on.</p>

<h3 id="4-the-glove-under-the-arm-drill">4. The Glove Under the Arm Drill</h3>

<p>Tuck a glove or headcover under your lead armpit. Make swings where it stays tucked through impact. This prevents your arms from flying away from your body early, which is often connected to casting.</p>

<h3 id="5-towel-whip-drill">5. Towel Whip Drill</h3>

<p>Swing a towel like a golf club. To make the end “crack” like a whip, you can’t throw it from the top—you have to sequence properly and let the end accelerate late.</p>

<p>This teaches the feel of stored and released energy without a club.</p>

<h2 id="what-to-look-for-in-video">What to Look for in Video</h2>

<p>When you <a href="/2026/01/19/record-your-golf-swing-phone-no-tripod/">record your swing</a>, freeze the video at these checkpoints:</p>

<p><strong>Transition (just starting down):</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>The wrist angle should be similar to what it was at the top</li>
  <li>Your hips should already be open (started rotating) while your shoulders are still relatively closed</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Hands at hip height (downswing):</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Look at the angle between your lead arm and the club shaft</li>
  <li>Tour pros still have 70-90 degrees of lag here</li>
  <li>Amateurs often have almost no angle left—the club has already straightened</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>At impact:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Hands should be ahead of the clubhead</li>
  <li>Shaft leans toward the target</li>
  <li>The wrist angle has released fully (the energy has been delivered)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="common-lag-myths">Common Lag Myths</h2>

<p><strong>Myth: You should feel like you’re “holding” the lag.</strong></p>

<p>Reality: Trying to hold the angle usually creates tension and awkward timing. Better players feel like they’re swinging freely, and lag happens naturally from good sequence.</p>

<p><strong>Myth: More lag is always better.</strong></p>

<p>Reality: There’s an optimal amount. Too much lag can actually cause timing issues and inconsistent contact. Focus on sequence, not maximizing the angle.</p>

<p><strong>Myth: Lag requires a specific wrist condition.</strong></p>

<p>Reality: Good lag comes from sequence and timing, not a particular wrist position. Both flat and slightly cupped lead wrists can produce excellent lag.</p>

<h2 id="the-real-secret-its-about-sequence">The Real Secret: It’s About Sequence</h2>

<p>Lag is a result, not a cause. You don’t create lag by focusing on your wrists. You create lag by:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Making a proper backswing with natural wrist hinge</li>
  <li>Starting the downswing from the ground up</li>
  <li>Letting your arms and club trail your body rotation</li>
  <li>Not trying to hit the ball—letting the release happen naturally</li>
</ol>

<p>When the sequence is right, lag appears automatically. When you try to manufacture it, you usually make things worse.</p>

<p>That’s why <a href="/2026/01/19/best-golf-swing-analyzer-app-2026/">video analysis</a> is so valuable for working on lag. You can’t feel what’s actually happening in fractions of a second. But you can see it, frame by frame, and train the right patterns.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>See your lag—or lack of it—in slow motion with <a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Swing Analyzer</a>. Frame-by-frame video analysis shows exactly where you’re losing power.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Swing Analyzer Team</name></author><category term="golf" /><category term="instruction" /><category term="golf lag" /><category term="golf power" /><category term="wrist hinge" /><category term="golf distance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn how to create and maintain lag in your golf swing for more distance with less effort. Understand what lag actually is and the drills that build it.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/creating-lag-golf-swing.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/creating-lag-golf-swing.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Fix Early Extension in Your Golf Swing: 6 Proven Drills</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-early-extension-golf-swing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Fix Early Extension in Your Golf Swing: 6 Proven Drills" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-early-extension-golf-swing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-early-extension-golf-swing/"><![CDATA[<p>Early extension is one of the most common and destructive swing flaws in golf. If you’ve ever hit a block to the right followed by a hook to the left, early extension might be the culprit. The good news? It’s fixable with the right understanding and drills.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-early-extension">What is Early Extension?</h2>

<p>Early extension is any forward movement (thrust) of your lower body toward the golf ball during the downswing. Instead of rotating around a stable spine, your hips push toward the ball, forcing your torso to stand up and your arms to get “stuck” behind your body.</p>

<p><strong>The result?</strong> Two frustrating misses:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The block</strong> (ball goes right) when your body outraces your arms</li>
  <li><strong>The hook</strong> (ball goes left) when your hands flip to compensate</li>
</ul>

<p>Having two opposite misses makes consistent golf nearly impossible.</p>

<h2 id="why-early-extension-happens">Why Early Extension Happens</h2>

<p>Understanding the root causes helps you target the right fix:</p>

<h3 id="physical-limitations">Physical Limitations</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Tight hips, hamstrings, or lower back</strong> - Research shows that any limitation in performing a full deep squat or hip bend can force early extension</li>
  <li><strong>Weak core muscles</strong> - Your core can’t stabilize your spine angle through impact</li>
  <li><strong>Poor mobility</strong> - You simply can’t maintain posture physically</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="swing-mechanics">Swing Mechanics</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Open clubface at the top</strong> - Your body instinctively tries to close it by standing up</li>
  <li><strong>Over-the-top swing path</strong> - Creates a chain reaction of compensations</li>
  <li><strong>Improper weight transfer</strong> - Failure to shift weight correctly forces the thrust</li>
  <li><strong>Fear of the ground</strong> - Subconscious avoidance of hitting the turf</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-power-problem">The Power Problem</h3>

<p>Early extension doesn’t just hurt accuracy - it costs you distance. When your hips extend toward the ball, you lose the stored rotational power that should transfer to the clubhead. You’re essentially “spending” your power too early.</p>

<h2 id="6-proven-drills-to-fix-early-extension">6 Proven Drills to Fix Early Extension</h2>

<h3 id="1-the-wall-drill-chair-drill">1. The Wall Drill (Chair Drill)</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Stand with your backside touching a wall or chair back at address.</p>

<p><strong>Execute:</strong> Make practice swings while maintaining contact with the wall throughout. Your glutes should stay against the wall from takeaway through impact.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> Forces your hips to rotate rather than thrust forward. You literally can’t early extend when your backside is anchored.</p>

<p><strong>Reps:</strong> 20-30 slow practice swings, then hit balls with the same feeling.</p>

<h3 id="2-the-head-on-wall-drill">2. The Head-on-Wall Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Stand as if addressing a ball with your forehead resting gently against a wall. No club needed.</p>

<p><strong>Execute:</strong> Make slow-motion swing movements while keeping your forehead on the wall throughout.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> If you early extend, your head will push off the wall as your spine angle changes. This drill gives you immediate feedback on posture loss.</p>

<p><strong>Reps:</strong> 15-20 repetitions, focusing on the feeling of maintaining spine angle.</p>

<h3 id="3-the-trail-foot-torque-drill">3. The Trail Foot Torque Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Place a wedge under your trail foot (right foot for right-handers), standing on the clubface with the grip pointing up.</p>

<p><strong>Execute:</strong> Make half-speed practice swings. Focus on keeping pressure on the wedge throughout.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> If you early extend, your heel lifts and the club falls. Proper hip rotation keeps the pressure on the club. This teaches you to use ground force correctly.</p>

<p><strong>Reps:</strong> 10-15 swings, building awareness of proper lower body action.</p>

<h3 id="4-the-split-grip-drill">4. The Split-Grip Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Hold the club with your hands separated - trail hand several inches below your lead hand on the grip.</p>

<p><strong>Execute:</strong> Make half-swings and try to make contact with the ball.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> The separated grip position makes it nearly impossible to early extend and still hit the ball. Your spine is forced into the correct position through impact.</p>

<p><strong>Reps:</strong> Hit 20 balls this way, then transition to normal grip with the same feeling.</p>

<h3 id="5-the-two-ball-drill">5. The Two-Ball Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Place two golf balls side by side, about 2 inches apart. Set up to the outside ball.</p>

<p><strong>Execute:</strong> Try to hit the inside ball.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> Made famous by instructor Monte Scheinblum, this drill forces you to stay back and rotate rather than thrust forward. If you early extend, you’ll hit the outside ball or miss entirely.</p>

<p><strong>Reps:</strong> Hit 15-20 balls, focusing on the inside target.</p>

<h3 id="6-the-belt-buckle-drill">6. The Belt Buckle Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Normal address position.</p>

<p><strong>Execute:</strong> Focus on keeping your belt buckle pointing at or slightly behind the ball through impact. Feel like you’re “covering” the ball with your chest.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> This mental cue prevents the premature hip thrust. Your lower body can still rotate powerfully while maintaining spine angle.</p>

<p><strong>Reps:</strong> Use this thought on every swing until it becomes automatic.</p>

<h2 id="physical-fixes-for-early-extension">Physical Fixes for Early Extension</h2>

<p>If your body is limiting your swing, these exercises help:</p>

<h3 id="flexibility-work">Flexibility Work</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Hip flexor stretches</strong> - Lunge stretches, 30 seconds each side</li>
  <li><strong>Hip rotations</strong> - 10-15 circles each direction, both legs</li>
  <li><strong>Hamstring stretches</strong> - Essential for maintaining posture</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="core-strengthening">Core Strengthening</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Planks</strong> - Build the stability to hold your spine angle</li>
  <li><strong>Russian twists</strong> - Rotational core strength</li>
  <li><strong>Medicine ball throws</strong> - Power transfer through a stable core</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="practice-tip">Practice Tip</h3>
<p>Before each range session, spend 5 minutes on hip mobility and a quick plank. Your body will be better prepared to maintain posture.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-know-youre-improving">How to Know You’re Improving</h2>

<p>Signs your early extension is getting better:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>More consistent miss direction</strong> - One-way misses are easier to manage</li>
  <li><strong>Better ball striking</strong> - More center contact</li>
  <li><strong>Hip rotation feels different</strong> - Spinning rather than thrusting</li>
  <li><strong>Less back pain</strong> - Early extension stresses the lower back</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="use-video-to-track-progress">Use Video to Track Progress</h2>

<p>Early extension is hard to feel but easy to see. <a href="/blog/phone-golf-swing-video/">Recording your swing with your phone</a> lets you see exactly what your hips are doing in the downswing.</p>

<p>Look for these checkpoints:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>At address</strong> - Note your hip distance from the ball</li>
  <li><strong>At impact</strong> - Hips should be in the same position or slightly farther from the ball</li>
  <li><strong>Through impact</strong> - Rotation around spine, not thrust toward ball</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Swing Analyzer</a> can help you track your posture through the swing, giving you objective feedback on whether you’re maintaining your spine angle or early extending.</p>

<h2 id="common-mistakes-when-fixing-early-extension">Common Mistakes When Fixing Early Extension</h2>

<p><strong>Don’t overcorrect by hanging back.</strong> Some golfers try so hard to avoid early extension that they keep their weight on the back foot. This causes fat shots and loss of power.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t stop your hips.</strong> Early extension isn’t about stopping hip movement - it’s about the <em>direction</em> of movement. Your hips should rotate powerfully; they just shouldn’t thrust forward.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t expect overnight fixes.</strong> Early extension is often a physical limitation combined with a swing habit. Both take time to change.</p>

<h2 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Early extension is fixable, but it requires understanding why you’re doing it:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Physical limitations</strong> - Address mobility and strength</li>
  <li><strong>Swing mechanics</strong> - Use drills to groove proper movement</li>
  <li><strong>Video feedback</strong> - You can’t fix what you can’t see</li>
</ol>

<p>Start with the Wall Drill and Split-Grip Drill - they give the most immediate feedback. Add the physical work if flexibility is an issue. And use <a href="/blog/how-ai-analyzes-golf-swing/">video analysis</a> to track your progress.</p>

<p>Your lower back will thank you, and your consistency will improve dramatically once you stop thrusting toward the ball.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Struggling to see your own early extension? <a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Swing Analyzer</a> provides instant AI-powered feedback on your swing, including posture throughout the motion. Try it free and see exactly what your hips are doing.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Swing Analyzer Team</name></author><category term="golf-instruction" /><category term="swing-fixes" /><category term="early-extension" /><category term="golf-swing" /><category term="posture" /><category term="drills" /><category term="consistency" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Early extension is destroying your consistency. Learn what causes this common swing flaw, why it leads to blocks and hooks, and 6 proven drills to fix it for good.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/early-extension-golf-swing.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/early-extension-golf-swing.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Fix an Over-the-Top Golf Swing: Causes and Drills That Work</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-over-the-top-golf-swing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Fix an Over-the-Top Golf Swing: Causes and Drills That Work" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-over-the-top-golf-swing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/fix-over-the-top-golf-swing/"><![CDATA[<p>The over-the-top move is the #1 swing flaw among amateur golfers. It causes slices, pulls, weak contact, and endless frustration. But here’s the good news: it’s fixable with the right understanding and drills.</p>

<h2 id="what-does-over-the-top-mean">What Does “Over the Top” Mean?</h2>

<p>Coming over the top means your club moves <strong>outside</strong> the ideal swing path during the downswing. Instead of dropping the club into the “slot” on an inside path, you throw it outward toward the ball. The result is a steep, out-to-in swing that produces:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Slices</strong> (ball curves hard right for right-handed golfers)</li>
  <li><strong>Pulls</strong> (ball starts left and stays left)</li>
  <li><strong>Weak pop-ups</strong> with the driver</li>
  <li><strong>Deep divots</strong> pointing left</li>
  <li>Loss of distance and consistency</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’re hitting pulls with short irons and slices with longer clubs, over the top is almost certainly your issue.</p>

<h2 id="the-root-causes">The Root Causes</h2>

<p>Understanding <em>why</em> you come over the top is essential to fixing it. The main culprits:</p>

<h3 id="1-arms-dominate-the-downswing">1. Arms Dominate the Downswing</h3>
<p>The most common cause. Instead of letting your lower body lead, you start the downswing by throwing your arms at the ball. This immediately pushes the club outside the proper path.</p>

<h3 id="2-poor-weight-transfer">2. Poor Weight Transfer</h3>
<p>If you stay stuck on your back foot, your body can’t rotate through properly. The arms have nowhere to go except over the top.</p>

<h3 id="3-early-hip-spin-instead-of-bump">3. Early Hip Spin (Instead of Bump)</h3>
<p>Some golfers spin their hips too early without shifting forward first. This stalls rotation and forces an over-the-top compensation.</p>

<h3 id="4-too-much-wrist-extension-at-the-top">4. Too Much Wrist Extension at the Top</h3>
<p>An excessively “cupped” wrist at the top can preset an over-the-top path. The club face opens, and you instinctively throw from outside to square it.</p>

<h3 id="5-wrong-mental-picture">5. Wrong Mental Picture</h3>
<p>Many golfers think they need to hit “down” on the ball, which creates a steep, outside attack. The reality is the club should approach from inside.</p>

<h2 id="7-drills-to-fix-over-the-top">7 Drills to Fix Over the Top</h2>

<h3 id="1-headcover-drill">1. Headcover Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Place a headcover 6-8 inches behind the ball, just outside your target line.</p>

<p><strong>Execution:</strong> On the downswing, feel your arms swing <em>under</em> the headcover. Your chest should stay “closed” longer as the club drops inside.</p>

<p><strong>Success check:</strong> If you hit the headcover, you came over the top. Keep practicing until you consistently miss it.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> Creates a visual barrier that forces you to find the inside path.</p>

<h3 id="2-trail-foot-flare">2. Trail Foot Flare</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Flare your trail foot (right foot for righties) 15-25 degrees open at address.</p>

<p><strong>Execution:</strong> Make your normal swing. The flared foot allows your hips to rotate more freely.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> Improved hip rotation creates more depth in your backswing, making it easier to drop the club inside on the downswing.</p>

<p>This is one of the simplest fixes—sometimes a setup change is all you need.</p>

<h3 id="3-hip-bump-with-alignment-stick">3. Hip Bump with Alignment Stick</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Place an alignment stick vertically in the ground. Position your front hip about an inch away from it at address.</p>

<p><strong>Execution:</strong> On the downswing, “bump” your front hip into the stick before your arms swing through.</p>

<p><strong>Success check:</strong> You should feel your hip touch the stick before the club reaches the ball.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> Forces proper sequencing—lower body leads, arms follow. This creates space for an inside path.</p>

<h3 id="4-ball-throwing-drill">4. Ball Throwing Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Hold a golf ball in your trail hand (right hand for righties).</p>

<p><strong>Execution:</strong> Make a backswing motion, then throw the ball <em>underhand</em> as if skipping it on water to your right (at 90 degrees from your target line).</p>

<p><strong>Success check:</strong> If the ball flies straight ahead or left, you’re coming over the top. Work until it naturally releases to the right.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> Teaches the feel of proper arm rotation and path without a club.</p>

<h3 id="5-pump-drill">5. Pump Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Take your normal address position.</p>

<p><strong>Execution:</strong> Make a backswing, then “pump” the club down halfway three times without hitting the ball. Feel the club drop into the slot each time. On the fourth pump, complete the swing.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> Builds muscle memory for the correct downswing initiation. The pumping motion reinforces the inside drop.</p>

<h3 id="6-feet-together-drill">6. Feet Together Drill</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Address an 8-iron with your feet completely together.</p>

<p><strong>Execution:</strong> Make half to three-quarter swings, hitting balls toward a target 75-100 yards away.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> With feet together, you can’t throw your body at the ball. Forces proper arm path and timing. If you come over the top with feet together, you’ll lose balance immediately.</p>

<h3 id="7-pause-at-the-top">7. Pause at the Top</h3>

<p><strong>Setup:</strong> Normal address position.</p>

<p><strong>Execution:</strong> Complete your backswing, pause for a full second at the top, then start down <em>slowly</em> with your hips before accelerating through impact.</p>

<p><strong>Why it works:</strong> The pause breaks the habit of rushing from the top with your arms. It gives you time to feel the lower body initiate.</p>

<h2 id="the-fix-in-practice">The Fix in Practice</h2>

<p>When working on your over-the-top move:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Start without a ball</strong> — Make dozens of slow practice swings feeling the inside path</li>
  <li><strong>Use half swings first</strong> — The shorter swing makes it easier to feel the correct sequence</li>
  <li><strong>Record your swing</strong> — <a href="/blog/video-golf-swing-analysis/">Swing Analyzer</a> can show you exactly where your club path is at each point</li>
  <li><strong>One drill at a time</strong> — Pick the drill that gives you the best “feel” and commit to it</li>
  <li><strong>Be patient</strong> — This flaw took years to develop; it won’t disappear in one range session</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="check-your-divots">Check Your Divots</h2>

<p>Your divot tells the truth. If your divot points left of target (for right-handed golfers), you’re still coming over the top. A neutral or slightly right-pointing divot indicates you’ve found an inside path.</p>

<p>See our guide on <a href="/blog/divot-patterns-golf/">reading divot patterns</a> for more on this diagnostic tool.</p>

<h2 id="the-connection-to-your-slice">The Connection to Your Slice</h2>

<p>If you slice the ball, over the top is likely the culprit. Check out our detailed guide on <a href="/blog/fix-golf-slice/">how to fix a golf slice</a> for more drills and fixes specific to eliminating the slice.</p>

<p>The over-the-top move and the slice are closely related, but not identical. You can come over the top and hit pulls (face closed) or slices (face open). Fixing the path is step one; face control is step two.</p>

<h2 id="video-analysis-helps">Video Analysis Helps</h2>

<p>One of the best ways to track your progress is recording your swing from down the line. This angle clearly shows whether your club is dropping inside or thrown outside. <a href="/blog/how-to-record-golf-swing-phone/">Learn how to record your swing</a> for accurate self-analysis.</p>

<p>Modern apps like Swing Analyzer can trace your club path and show you exactly where the over-the-top move happens, making it easier to target your practice.</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>The over-the-top swing is common but fixable. Key points:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>It’s a sequencing issue</strong> — arms fire before lower body</li>
  <li><strong>Multiple causes</strong> — identify yours for targeted improvement</li>
  <li><strong>Drills work</strong> — but commit to one or two rather than trying everything</li>
  <li><strong>Record your progress</strong> — video doesn’t lie</li>
  <li><strong>Patience required</strong> — ingrained habits take time to change</li>
</ul>

<p>With consistent practice using these drills, you can eliminate the over-the-top move and start hitting straighter, more powerful shots.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Ready to see your swing path in detail? <a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Try Swing Analyzer</a> for AI-powered feedback on your downswing sequence and club path.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Swing Analyzer Team</name></author><category term="instruction" /><category term="swing-fixes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stop slicing and pulling shots with this complete guide to fixing your over-the-top golf swing. Learn the root causes and 7 proven drills to get your club on the right path.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/fix-over-the-top-golf-swing.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/fix-over-the-top-golf-swing.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Golf Ball Position Guide: Where to Place the Ball for Every Club</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-ball-position-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Golf Ball Position Guide: Where to Place the Ball for Every Club" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-ball-position-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-ball-position-guide/"><![CDATA[<p>Ball position might be the most overlooked fundamental in golf. You spend hours perfecting your swing, but if the ball is in the wrong spot at address, you are fighting a losing battle before the club even moves.</p>

<p>The good news? Once you understand where to place the ball for each club, you will make better contact immediately. No swing changes required.</p>

<h2 id="why-ball-position-matters">Why Ball Position Matters</h2>

<p>Ball position directly affects three critical factors in your shot:</p>

<p><strong>Contact Quality</strong>: Position the ball too far forward and you will catch it thin or top it entirely. Too far back and you will chunk it into the turf. The correct position puts the ball exactly where your swing naturally bottoms out.</p>

<p><strong>Launch Angle and Trajectory</strong>: Forward ball positions create higher launch. Back positions create lower, more penetrating shots. This is physics, not opinion.</p>

<p><strong>Shot Shape</strong>: Ball position influences whether you hit draws or fades. A ball too far forward tends to produce pulls and hooks. Too far back leads to pushes and slices.</p>

<p>Understanding these relationships lets you dial in consistent contact and predictable ball flight. It also gives you tools to adjust trajectory when conditions demand it.</p>

<h2 id="ball-position-for-every-club-in-your-bag">Ball Position for Every Club in Your Bag</h2>

<p>Here is your complete reference guide, starting with the longest clubs and working down to wedges.</p>

<h3 id="driver-inside-your-front-heel">Driver: Inside Your Front Heel</h3>

<p>Your driver requires the most forward ball position of any club. Place the ball just inside your front heel, opposite your big toe on the lead foot.</p>

<p>Why so far forward? The driver is the only club you want to hit on the upswing. That ascending strike launches the ball higher with less spin, maximizing distance. Position it too far back and you will hit down on it, creating excess spin and losing yards.</p>

<p>A common mistake is playing the driver too far forward, past the front heel. This causes topped shots, pop-ups, and hooks as you reach for the ball at impact.</p>

<p>For more on optimizing your tee shots, check out our guide to <a href="/2026/01/29/golf-driver-tips/">hitting longer, straighter drives</a>.</p>

<h3 id="fairway-woods-and-hybrids-one-to-two-balls-back">Fairway Woods and Hybrids: One to Two Balls Back</h3>

<p>Fairway woods and hybrids sit about one to two ball widths back from your driver position. This puts them roughly opposite the logo on your shirt or just inside your front armpit.</p>

<p>These clubs need a slightly descending or level strike. You want to sweep the ball cleanly off the turf or tee. Too far forward and you will catch them thin. Too far back and you will dig into the ground before making contact.</p>

<p>Hybrids are particularly sensitive to ball position. Many golfers play them too far back like an iron, which causes fat shots. Keep them closer to your fairway wood position and let the club design do its job.</p>

<h3 id="long-irons-3-5-iron-center-forward">Long Irons (3-5 Iron): Center-Forward</h3>

<p>Long irons should sit about one to two inches forward of center, roughly in line with your shirt logo or the inside of your front armpit.</p>

<p>You need a descending blow with irons, but long irons require a shallower angle of attack than short irons. This forward position lets you compress the ball while still catching it cleanly.</p>

<p>If you struggle with long irons, ball position is often the culprit. Move it too far back and you will never get these clubs airborne consistently.</p>

<h3 id="mid-irons-6-7-iron-just-forward-of-center">Mid Irons (6-7 Iron): Just Forward of Center</h3>

<p>Your mid irons belong about one inch forward of the center of your stance. Think of a spot between your sternum and shirt logo.</p>

<p>This position promotes the ball-first contact that creates that satisfying divot after the ball. You are hitting down through the shot, compressing the ball against the turf for maximum control.</p>

<h3 id="short-irons-and-wedges-8-iron-through-lob-wedge-center">Short Irons and Wedges (8-Iron through Lob Wedge): Center</h3>

<p>Short irons and wedges should be positioned at or very near the center of your stance. Some players prefer them slightly back of center for even more control.</p>

<p>These clubs demand the steepest angle of attack. Center position lets you drive down through the ball aggressively, creating the backspin that stops shots on the green.</p>

<p>For specialty wedge shots around the green, you might move the ball slightly back for lower trajectories or forward for higher, softer landings.</p>

<h2 id="common-ball-position-mistakes">Common Ball Position Mistakes</h2>

<p>Even experienced golfers fall into these traps. Here is what to watch for.</p>

<h3 id="ball-too-far-forward">Ball Too Far Forward</h3>

<p>When the ball creeps too far forward in your stance, several bad things happen:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Thin shots</strong>: Your swing arc bottoms out before reaching the ball, catching it on the upswing with the leading edge</li>
  <li><strong>Pulls and hooks</strong>: You have to release the club early to reach the ball, closing the face through impact</li>
  <li><strong>Loss of compression</strong>: You cannot hit down on the ball properly, losing distance and control</li>
</ul>

<p>If you are hitting thin shots and pulls, check your ball position first. It is probably too far forward for the club in your hands.</p>

<p>Our guide on <a href="/2026/01/23/stop-fat-thin-shots/">fixing fat and thin shots</a> covers this in detail.</p>

<h3 id="ball-too-far-back">Ball Too Far Back</h3>

<p>The opposite problem creates its own set of issues:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Fat shots</strong>: Your swing bottoms out before the ball, driving the club into the turf</li>
  <li><strong>Pushes and blocks</strong>: You cannot square the face in time, leaving it open at impact</li>
  <li><strong>Low trajectory</strong>: You deloft the club excessively, hitting line drives when you need height</li>
</ul>

<p>Fat shots and pushes often trace back to ball position that has drifted too far back.</p>

<h3 id="inconsistent-position">Inconsistent Position</h3>

<p>Perhaps the biggest mistake is not having a consistent ball position at all. Many golfers eyeball it differently every time, creating random contact patterns.</p>

<p>Your brain cannot learn to time impact correctly if the ball moves around. Establish consistent reference points and use them every single time you address a shot.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-check-your-ball-position">How to Check Your Ball Position</h2>

<p>Guessing leads to inconsistency. Here are two proven methods to verify your ball position.</p>

<h3 id="the-alignment-stick-drill">The Alignment Stick Drill</h3>

<p>This is the gold standard for ball position practice:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Place an alignment stick on the ground pointing at your target</li>
  <li>Place a second stick perpendicular to the first, running between your feet</li>
  <li>Position the ball where the sticks intersect</li>
  <li>Step into your stance and check where the ball sits relative to your feet</li>
</ol>

<p>The perpendicular stick shows you exactly where center is. From there, you can accurately measure forward or back positions for different clubs.</p>

<p>Use this drill regularly on the range until correct positions become automatic. For more on using alignment aids effectively, see our <a href="/2026/01/23/golf-alignment-aim/">complete alignment guide</a>.</p>

<h3 id="the-foot-check-method">The Foot-Check Method</h3>

<p>For a quick check without equipment:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Address the ball as normal</li>
  <li>Without moving your feet, bring your hands together in front of your body</li>
  <li>Let your hands hang naturally from your shoulders</li>
  <li>Look down and note where your hands point relative to the ball</li>
</ol>

<p>Your hands naturally hang at the center of your stance. If the ball is forward of your hands, it is forward of center. If it is behind your hands, it is back of center.</p>

<p>This works great for mid-round adjustments when you cannot lay down alignment sticks.</p>

<h2 id="ball-position-for-special-situations">Ball Position for Special Situations</h2>

<p>Standard positions work for flat lies and normal conditions. But golf rarely gives you perfect circumstances.</p>

<h3 id="uphill-lies">Uphill Lies</h3>

<p>On uphill lies, move the ball slightly forward in your stance. The slope effectively tilts your swing arc forward, so the ball needs to move with it.</p>

<p>Also widen your stance for stability and expect higher trajectory with less distance.</p>

<h3 id="downhill-lies">Downhill Lies</h3>

<p>Downhill lies require the opposite adjustment. Move the ball back in your stance to account for the slope tilting your swing arc backward.</p>

<p>Expect lower trajectory and more roll. Take one less club and plan for the ball to run.</p>

<h3 id="windy-conditions">Windy Conditions</h3>

<p>When you need to flight the ball lower into the wind, move it back in your stance by one to two ball widths. This naturally delofts the club and produces a more penetrating trajectory.</p>

<p>Combine this with a shorter backswing and smooth tempo. Fighting the wind with a harder swing just creates more spin and balloons the shot higher.</p>

<h3 id="tight-lies">Tight Lies</h3>

<p>On hardpan or tight lies where there is no grass cushion, play the ball slightly back of your normal position. This steeper angle of attack helps you catch the ball cleanly without bouncing the club off the hard surface.</p>

<h2 id="building-your-pre-shot-routine">Building Your Pre-Shot Routine</h2>

<p>Ball position should be part of a consistent <a href="/2026/01/30/golf-pre-shot-routine/">pre-shot routine</a>. Here is a simple approach:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Stand behind the ball and pick your target line</li>
  <li>Walk to the ball from the side, setting the clubface first</li>
  <li>Position your feet using a consistent reference point</li>
  <li>Take one look at the target and swing</li>
</ol>

<p>The key is making ball position automatic, not something you think about over every shot. Build it into your routine and trust it.</p>

<h2 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Correct ball position is not complicated, but it demands attention. Here is your quick reference:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Driver</strong>: Inside front heel</li>
  <li><strong>Fairway woods and hybrids</strong>: One to two balls back from driver</li>
  <li><strong>Long irons</strong>: Center-forward</li>
  <li><strong>Mid irons</strong>: Just forward of center</li>
  <li><strong>Short irons and wedges</strong>: Center</li>
</ul>

<p>Get these positions dialed in and you will make better contact without changing anything else in your swing. That is the kind of improvement every golfer can use.</p>

<h2 id="see-your-ball-position-at-address">See Your Ball Position at Address</h2>

<p>Want to verify your ball position is correct? Swing Analyzer’s video analysis shows you exactly where the ball sits relative to your stance at address. Upload a face-on video and see your setup from a perspective you cannot get on your own. In 90 seconds, you will know if ball position is helping or hurting your swing.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Ball position affects everything from contact to trajectory to shot shape. Get it right and the rest of your swing has a chance to work. Get it wrong and you are compensating before the club even moves.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Swing Analyzer Team</name></author><category term="instruction" /><category term="fundamentals" /><category term="ball position" /><category term="setup" /><category term="fundamentals" /><category term="irons" /><category term="driver" /><category term="wedges" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn the correct golf ball position for driver, irons, and wedges. Master ball placement to improve contact, trajectory, and distance on every shot.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-ball-position-guide.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-ball-position-guide.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Golf Course Management: The Smart Strategy Guide to Lower Scores</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-course-management-strategy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Golf Course Management: The Smart Strategy Guide to Lower Scores" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-course-management-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-course-management-strategy/"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s a humbling statistic: according to Shot Scope data, average recreational golfers miss greens short 54% of the time. Not left. Not right. Not long. Short.</p>

<p>This isn’t a swing problem—it’s a course management problem. Most amateurs don’t know their true distances, overestimate their abilities, and compound these errors with poor target selection.</p>

<p>The fastest way to drop 3-5 strokes from your scores isn’t a new swing thought—it’s smarter decision-making on every shot.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-course-management">What Is Course Management?</h2>

<p>Course management is the art of making decisions that maximize your scoring probability. It includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Club selection</strong> based on realistic distances</li>
  <li><strong>Target picking</strong> that accounts for your tendencies</li>
  <li><strong>Risk-reward assessment</strong> on every shot</li>
  <li><strong>Recovery strategy</strong> when things go wrong</li>
  <li><strong>Mental approach</strong> throughout the round</li>
</ul>

<p>The best course managers aren’t always the best ball-strikers. They simply avoid mistakes that turn pars into bogeys and bogeys into doubles.</p>

<h2 id="the-foundation-know-your-true-distances">The Foundation: Know Your True Distances</h2>

<p>Most scoring leaks stem from distance delusion. Here’s how to build an honest distance chart.</p>

<h3 id="carry-distance-vs-total-distance">Carry Distance vs. Total Distance</h3>

<p>Your carry distance is what matters for course management—total distance includes roll, which varies by conditions. Track carry, not total.</p>

<h3 id="real-yardages-not-best-case-scenarios">Real Yardages, Not Best-Case Scenarios</h3>

<p>Stop measuring distances from your career-best shots. Tour pros base club selection on their <strong>80th percentile</strong> distance—the distance they hit or exceed 80% of the time.</p>

<p>Your real 7-iron isn’t that one time you caught it pure on a downhill lie with helping wind. It’s what you hit when you’re slightly off-center, which is most swings.</p>

<h3 id="building-your-distance-chart">Building Your Distance Chart</h3>

<p>Spend a range session tracking actual carry distances:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Club</th>
      <th>Your Carry</th>
      <th>(Example)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>PW</td>
      <td>_____</td>
      <td>120 yards</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9i</td>
      <td>_____</td>
      <td>130 yards</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8i</td>
      <td>_____</td>
      <td>140 yards</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7i</td>
      <td>_____</td>
      <td>150 yards</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>6i</td>
      <td>_____</td>
      <td>160 yards</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5i</td>
      <td>_____</td>
      <td>170 yards</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Use a launch monitor or GPS app to get accurate numbers. <a href="/blog/how-ai-analyzes-golf-swings/">AI golf swing analyzers</a> can also track your distances over time. Once you know your real distances, club selection becomes simple math instead of hopeful guessing.</p>

<h2 id="why-you-miss-greens-short">Why You Miss Greens Short</h2>

<p>The 54% short miss rate comes from several compounding errors:</p>

<h3 id="1-distance-overestimation">1. Distance Overestimation</h3>
<p>Most golfers think they hit clubs 10-15 yards farther than they actually do. A golfer who thinks their 7-iron goes 160 yards but actually carries 145 will miss short constantly.</p>

<h3 id="2-middle-of-green-aiming">2. Middle-of-Green Aiming</h3>
<p>When the pin is back, aiming at the center of the green is actually aiming short of the hole. Your “miss” is programmed in before you swing.</p>

<h3 id="3-failure-to-account-for-conditions">3. Failure to Account for Conditions</h3>
<p>Cold air, elevation, wind, and humidity all affect distance. A shot that carries 150 yards in summer might only go 140 in cold weather.</p>

<h3 id="4-safety-bias">4. Safety Bias</h3>
<p>Golfers subconsciously fear going long (often there’s trouble behind greens), so they unconsciously take off power. The result: consistent short misses.</p>

<p><strong>The Fix</strong>: Pick a club that gets you to the back of the green on a centered strike. If you catch it slightly thin, you still hit the putting surface. If you pure it, you’re on the back—but still on.</p>

<h2 id="target-selection-where-you-aim-matters">Target Selection: Where You Aim Matters</h2>

<h3 id="dont-aim-at-flagsaim-at-zones">Don’t Aim at Flags—Aim at Zones</h3>

<p>Pin-seeking from 150 yards is ego golf. Tour pros aim at specific quadrants of greens based on:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Pin location</li>
  <li>Miss tendency</li>
  <li>Green contours</li>
  <li>Surrounding hazards</li>
</ul>

<p>As an amateur, your target should usually be the <strong>fat part of the green</strong>. A 30-foot putt beats a chip from a bunker every time.</p>

<h3 id="account-for-your-curve">Account for Your Curve</h3>

<p>If you typically fade the ball 10 yards, your aim point needs to be 10 yards left of your target. Yet most golfers aim at the target and watch the ball curve into trouble.</p>

<p><strong>Right-handed fader</strong>: Aim at the left third of the green
<strong>Right-handed drawer</strong>: Aim at the right third of the green</p>

<p>Your curve is a feature, not a bug—but only if you account for it.</p>

<h3 id="danger-zone-mapping">Danger Zone Mapping</h3>

<p>Before each approach, identify:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Where is the <strong>worst miss</strong>? (deep bunker, water, OB)</li>
  <li>Where is the <strong>acceptable miss</strong>? (fringe, shallow rough)</li>
  <li>What aim point eliminates the worst outcome?</li>
</ol>

<p>The goal isn’t a perfect shot—it’s eliminating disaster.</p>

<h2 id="the-risk-reward-framework">The Risk-Reward Framework</h2>

<p>Every shot involves a risk-reward calculation. Smart golfers make conscious choices instead of hoping for the best.</p>

<h3 id="the-60-rule">The 60% Rule</h3>

<p>Only attempt a shot if you can execute it successfully at least 60% of the time. This includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Carrying that bunker on a 220-yard approach</li>
  <li>Threading between trees on a recovery shot</li>
  <li>Going for a par-5 in two</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’d fail more often than you’d succeed, take the safer option.</p>

<h3 id="par-5-math">Par-5 Math</h3>

<p>Going for the green in two feels heroic, but let’s examine the math:</p>

<p><strong>Aggressive play</strong> (going for it):</p>
<ul>
  <li>30% chance of reaching green, average result = birdie (4)</li>
  <li>40% chance of just missing, average result = par (5)</li>
  <li>30% chance of hazard/trouble, average result = bogey+ (6+)</li>
  <li>Expected score: ~5.1</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Conservative play</strong> (laying up):</p>
<ul>
  <li>80% chance of 100-yard wedge approach</li>
  <li>Average result = par/bogey (5.2)</li>
  <li>No blow-up potential</li>
  <li>Expected score: ~5.2</li>
</ul>

<p>The numbers are closer than you’d think—and conservative play has lower variance. Save aggressive plays for when you’re actually hot.</p>

<h3 id="when-to-take-risk">When to Take Risk</h3>

<ul>
  <li>You’re significantly behind in match play</li>
  <li>Wind or conditions favor the aggressive line</li>
  <li>The “safe” play isn’t actually safe</li>
  <li>You’re in a good mental state and playing well</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="when-to-play-safe">When to Play Safe</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Any time the risk is OB or water</li>
  <li>You haven’t been striking it well</li>
  <li>The hole is playing hard for the field</li>
  <li>One mistake ends your round (tournament golf)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="tee-shot-strategy">Tee Shot Strategy</h2>

<h3 id="driver-isnt-always-right">Driver Isn’t Always Right</h3>

<p>The goal of a tee shot is positioning for the approach, not maximum distance. Consider:</p>
<ul>
  <li>What distance leaves your favorite approach yardage?</li>
  <li>Is driver’s extra distance worth its extra dispersion?</li>
  <li>Where is the trouble, and what club avoids it?</li>
</ul>

<p>On a 380-yard hole with trouble at 260 yards, a 240-yard 3-wood leaves 140 yards—a controlled 8-iron. Driver might leave 100 yards, but if one miss puts you in hazard or trees, the 3-wood is smarter.</p>

<h3 id="picking-your-side">Picking Your Side</h3>

<p>Tee boxes let you choose your angle. If trouble is right:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Tee up on the right side</li>
  <li>Aim away from trouble</li>
  <li>Your natural curve should turn away from danger</li>
</ul>

<p>Most amateurs tee up randomly. Pros are intentional about every setup variable.</p>

<h2 id="recovery-strategy">Recovery Strategy</h2>

<p>You’ll hit bad shots. Course management determines whether they become bogeys or double-bogeys.</p>

<h3 id="the-golden-rule-of-recovery">The Golden Rule of Recovery</h3>

<p><strong>Get the ball back in play. Period.</strong></p>

<p>The hero shot from trouble that looks cool on TV? Tour pros attempt those because they execute them. Your job is to minimize damage and give yourself a chance at bogey.</p>

<h3 id="the-90-degree-rule">The 90-Degree Rule</h3>

<p>When you’re in trees or trouble, the first priority is getting out—even if that means going sideways or slightly backwards. A 90-degree punch to the fairway beats a tree-ricocheting attempt that leaves you in more trouble.</p>

<h3 id="calculate-your-real-options">Calculate Your Real Options</h3>

<p>From trouble, honestly assess:</p>
<ol>
  <li>What’s the probability I can advance toward the green?</li>
  <li>What happens if I miss the tight window?</li>
  <li>Is there a 100% escape route that sets up a short-game opportunity?</li>
</ol>

<p>Taking medicine early (accepting one stroke of penalty) often saves two or three strokes compared to compounding errors.</p>

<h2 id="mental-course-management">Mental Course Management</h2>

<h3 id="process-over-outcome">Process Over Outcome</h3>

<p>Developing a solid <a href="/blog/golf-pre-shot-routine/">pre-shot routine</a> helps you execute good decisions consistently. You can make a great decision and hit a good shot that yields a bad result (wind gust, unlucky bounce). Conversely, you can make a terrible decision and get lucky.</p>

<p>Judge your course management by your process, not individual outcomes. Over time, good process yields good results.</p>

<h3 id="the-fresh-start-mentality">The Fresh-Start Mentality</h3>

<p>After a bad hole, many golfers press harder on the next one—trying to “get the stroke back.” This leads to aggressive decisions and more mistakes.</p>

<p>Each hole is independent. Your previous result doesn’t change the optimal strategy for the current shot. Reset mentally.</p>

<h3 id="pre-round-preparation">Pre-Round Preparation</h3>

<p>Before your round:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Review the scorecard and note tricky holes</li>
  <li>Identify where trouble is (course map or GPS)</li>
  <li>Plan your tee shot strategy for each hole</li>
  <li>Note which holes you’ll play aggressively vs. conservatively</li>
</ol>

<p>Having a plan removes in-the-moment emotional decisions.</p>

<h2 id="putting-course-management-in-practice">Putting Course Management in Practice</h2>

<h3 id="practice-rounds">Practice Rounds</h3>

<p>During casual rounds, experiment with course management:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Hit 3-wood instead of driver and note results</li>
  <li>Aim at green centers instead of pins</li>
  <li>Take the safe option on every risk-reward hole</li>
  <li>Track how often you avoid big numbers</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="shot-tracking">Shot Tracking</h3>

<p>Record decisions, not just scores:</p>
<ul>
  <li>What club did you hit?</li>
  <li>What was your target?</li>
  <li>What was the result?</li>
  <li>Was the decision smart given the outcome?</li>
</ul>

<p>Patterns emerge: maybe you succeed 70% when going for it from 200 yards but only 30% from 230 yards. Data drives better future decisions.</p>

<h3 id="using-technology">Using Technology</h3>

<p>Modern <a href="/best-golf-swing-analyzer-app-2026">golf swing analyzer apps</a> and GPS apps provide data that supports better course management:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Accurate carry distances from practice</li>
  <li>Hole layouts with hazard distances</li>
  <li>Shot tracking and pattern analysis</li>
</ul>

<p>The same technology that analyzes your swing can help you make smarter choices on the course.</p>

<h2 id="the-course-management-mindset">The Course Management Mindset</h2>

<p>Playing smart golf isn’t boring golf—it’s winning golf. The most satisfying rounds often involve fewer spectacular shots and more solid, boring pars.</p>

<p>When you stop trying to manufacture career-best shots on every swing and start maximizing your probability of scoring well, you’ll discover a new level of consistency. And lower scores.</p>

<p>The next time you reach for driver on a tight hole or aim at a sucker pin, pause. Ask yourself: what decision gives me the best chance to walk off this green with a good number?</p>

<p>That’s course management—and it might be the fastest improvement tool in your bag.</p>

<p><strong>Related Posts:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="/2026/01/29/golf-driver-tips/">Golf Driver Tips: 7 Keys to Longer, Straighter Drives</a></li>
  <li><a href="/2026/01/30/wedge-distance-control-guide/">Wedge Distance Control: Dial In Your Scoring Clubs</a></li>
  <li><a href="/2026/01/30/golf-pre-shot-routine/">Golf Pre-Shot Routine: Build Confidence and Consistency</a></li>
  <li><a href="/2026/01/29/psychology-of-golf-practice/">The Psychology of Golf Practice: Why Fun Matters</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Fulcria Labs</name></author><category term="instruction" /><category term="strategy" /><category term="course management" /><category term="strategy" /><category term="scoring" /><category term="mental game" /><category term="shot selection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn golf course management strategies that pros use. Master club selection, target picking, risk-reward decisions, and mental tactics to shoot lower scores without changing your swing.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-course-management-strategy.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-course-management-strategy.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Golf Etiquette Guide: 15 Rules Every Golfer Should Know</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-etiquette-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Golf Etiquette Guide: 15 Rules Every Golfer Should Know" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-etiquette-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-etiquette-guide/"><![CDATA[<p>Golf etiquette might seem intimidating when you’re new to the game, but these unwritten rules exist for good reason. They ensure everyone enjoys their round, the course stays in great condition, and play moves efficiently. Master these guidelines and you’ll feel confident stepping onto any course.</p>

<h2 id="why-golf-etiquette-matters">Why Golf Etiquette Matters</h2>

<p>Unlike most sports, golf relies heavily on self-regulation. There are no referees watching your every move. The game’s traditions of honesty, respect, and consideration for others are what make it unique. Good etiquette shows respect for fellow players, the course, and the game itself.</p>

<p>Think of etiquette as the social contract of golf. When everyone follows these principles, the experience improves for everyone.</p>

<h2 id="on-the-tee-box">On the Tee Box</h2>

<h3 id="1-arrive-early-and-be-ready">1. Arrive Early and Be Ready</h3>

<p>Show up at least 15 minutes before your tee time. This gives you time to warm up, check in, and be ready when your group is called. Nothing starts a round worse than rushing to the first tee unprepared.</p>

<p>Have your ball, tees, and club ready when it’s your turn. While others hit, you can take practice swings (away from them) and visualize your shot.</p>

<h3 id="2-the-quiet-zone">2. The Quiet Zone</h3>

<p>When someone is addressing their ball or swinging, absolute silence is expected. This means:</p>
<ul>
  <li>No talking or whispering</li>
  <li>No movement in their peripheral vision</li>
  <li>No rustling through your bag</li>
  <li>No phone sounds</li>
</ul>

<p>Stand still and out of their line of sight. If you’re in their peripheral vision, they might ask you to move—don’t take offense.</p>

<h3 id="3-honors-and-order-of-play">3. Honors and Order of Play</h3>

<p>The player with the lowest score on the previous hole has “honors” and tees off first. On the first hole, you can flip a tee or decide among yourselves.</p>

<p>After the tee shot, the player farthest from the hole plays next. This continues until everyone holes out.</p>

<h2 id="pace-of-play">Pace of Play</h2>

<h3 id="4-keep-up-with-the-group-ahead">4. Keep Up with the Group Ahead</h3>

<p>This is the most important etiquette rule in modern golf. Your goal is to keep up with the group in front of you, not stay ahead of the group behind you.</p>

<p>Tips for good pace:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Walk briskly between shots</li>
  <li>Start planning your shot as you approach your ball</li>
  <li>Limit practice swings to one or two</li>
  <li>Pick up if you’re struggling on a hole (recreational golf)</li>
  <li>Play “ready golf” when appropriate</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="5-ready-golf">5. Ready Golf</h3>

<p>In casual play, “ready golf” means whoever is ready plays first, regardless of who’s away. This is now encouraged by the USGA and R&amp;A to speed up play.</p>

<p>Safe ready golf practices:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Hit when it’s safe and you won’t disturb others</li>
  <li>Let faster groups play through</li>
  <li>Don’t wait to walk to your ball while others are hitting</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="6-let-faster-groups-play-through">6. Let Faster Groups Play Through</h3>

<p>If you’re falling behind and the group behind is waiting, let them play through. This isn’t an insult—it’s good etiquette. Simply wave them up on a tee box or at a convenient point.</p>

<h2 id="course-care">Course Care</h2>

<h3 id="7-repair-your-ball-marks">7. Repair Your Ball Marks</h3>

<p>Every time your ball lands on the green and creates an indentation, repair it immediately. Use a repair tool or tee:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Insert at an angle around the mark’s edges</li>
  <li>Push toward the center</li>
  <li>Smooth with your putter</li>
</ul>

<p>Unrepaired ball marks take weeks to heal and can affect putts. Repair one extra while you’re at it to offset those who don’t.</p>

<h3 id="8-replace-your-divots">8. Replace Your Divots</h3>

<p>When you take a divot with an iron, you have two options depending on the course:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Replace the divot and step on it gently</li>
  <li>Fill with sand/seed mixture (if provided on carts)</li>
</ul>

<p>Ask the pro shop which method your course prefers.</p>

<h3 id="9-rake-the-bunkers">9. Rake the Bunkers</h3>

<p>After escaping a bunker, rake it smooth for the next player. The general approach:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Enter and exit from the low side when possible</li>
  <li>Rake your footprints and shot marks</li>
  <li>Leave the rake as the course indicates (inside or outside the bunker)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="10-respect-cart-rules">10. Respect Cart Rules</h3>

<p>If using a cart, follow all cart path rules and signs. Common rules include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>90-degree rule: Drive on the path, then turn 90 degrees to your ball</li>
  <li>Cart path only: Stay on paths due to wet conditions</li>
  <li>Keep carts away from greens and tees</li>
</ul>

<p>Walking is often better for both your game and the course.</p>

<h2 id="on-the-green">On the Green</h2>

<h3 id="11-dont-step-in-someones-line">11. Don’t Step in Someone’s Line</h3>

<p>The “line” is the path between a player’s ball and the hole. Never step on or across someone’s putting line. Walk around, even if it’s the long way.</p>

<p>Also be aware of the line past the hole—if they miss, that becomes their new line.</p>

<h3 id="12-tend-the-flagstick-properly">12. Tend the Flagstick Properly</h3>

<p>If you’re tending the pin for another player:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Stand at arm’s length, not blocking their line</li>
  <li>Hold the flag to prevent it from flapping</li>
  <li>Remove it after they strike the ball</li>
  <li>Don’t let your shadow cross their line</li>
</ul>

<p>With the 2019 rule change, players can now putt with the flag in. Ask your playing partners their preference.</p>

<h3 id="13-mark-your-ball-correctly">13. Mark Your Ball Correctly</h3>

<p>Place a coin or ball marker directly behind your ball before picking it up. If your marker is in someone’s line, offer to move it a putter-head or two to the side. Just remember to move it back before putting.</p>

<h2 id="general-conduct">General Conduct</h2>

<h3 id="14-control-your-emotions">14. Control Your Emotions</h3>

<p>Golf is frustrating. Even professionals struggle to control their temper. But throwing clubs, excessive cursing, or angry outbursts have no place on the course.</p>

<p>Take a breath. Remember why you play—for enjoyment and the challenge. Your playing partners don’t deserve to share your bad mood.</p>

<h3 id="15-safety-first">15. Safety First</h3>

<p>Always yell “FORE!” loudly if your ball might hit someone. Better to embarrass yourself with a false alarm than injure another player.</p>

<p>Never hit while others might be in range. Wait for the group ahead to be well out of distance, even if you think you can’t reach them. (You might hit the best shot of your life at the worst possible moment.)</p>

<h2 id="mobile-phone-etiquette">Mobile Phone Etiquette</h2>

<p>Keep your phone on silent. If you must take a call, step away from your group and keep it brief. Never take calls while someone is hitting.</p>

<p>Phones for playing music are increasingly common but remain controversial. If you play music, keep it low and ask your group if they mind.</p>

<h2 id="what-happens-when-you-make-a-mistake">What Happens When You Make a Mistake</h2>

<p>Everyone violates etiquette occasionally, even experienced players. If you make a mistake:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Apologize sincerely</li>
  <li>Learn from it</li>
  <li>Move on without excessive self-criticism</li>
</ul>

<p>If you see a beginner making etiquette errors, gently and privately offer guidance. We were all new once.</p>

<h2 id="the-spirit-of-the-game">The Spirit of the Game</h2>

<p>Beyond these specific rules, golf etiquette comes down to three principles:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Respect for others</strong>: Your actions affect fellow players</li>
  <li><strong>Respect for the course</strong>: Leave it better than you found it</li>
  <li><strong>Respect for the game</strong>: Honor its traditions of honesty and sportsmanship</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="practice-your-game-know-the-rules">Practice Your Game, Know the Rules</h2>

<p>Good etiquette becomes second nature with experience. Pair it with solid fundamentals in your swing—check out our guides on <a href="/2026/01/30/golf-swing-basics-beginners-guide/">golf swing basics</a> and <a href="/2026/01/30/golf-course-management-strategy/">course management strategy</a> for a complete foundation.</p>

<p>Recording your swing with tools like <a href="https://swing.fulcria.com">Swing Analyzer</a> helps you improve faster so you can focus less on your mechanics and more on enjoying the game with your playing partners.</p>

<h2 id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Keep up with the group ahead—pace of play matters most</li>
  <li>Stay quiet and still when others are hitting</li>
  <li>Repair ball marks, replace divots, rake bunkers</li>
  <li>Never walk in someone’s putting line</li>
  <li>Yell “FORE!” if your ball might hit anyone</li>
  <li>Keep your phone silent and emotions in check</li>
</ul>

<p>Golf is called a gentleman’s game (or gentleperson’s game) for a reason. These etiquette principles are what separate it from every other sport. Follow them, and you’ll be welcome on any course in the world.</p>]]></content><author><name>Swing Analyzer Team</name></author><category term="Golf Basics" /><category term="Beginner Guide" /><category term="golf etiquette" /><category term="golf rules" /><category term="beginner golf" /><category term="golf course behavior" /><category term="golf manners" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Master essential golf etiquette with our comprehensive guide. Learn the unwritten rules of pace of play, course care, and on-course behavior that every golfer needs to know.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-etiquette-guide.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-etiquette-guide.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Golf Iron Tips: How to Hit Your Irons Pure Every Time</title><link href="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-iron-tips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Golf Iron Tips: How to Hit Your Irons Pure Every Time" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-iron-tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/blog/golf-iron-tips/"><![CDATA[<p>Irons are the scoring clubs. You can recover from a wayward drive, but inconsistent iron play bleeds strokes all day long. The difference between a 90s golfer and an 80s golfer often comes down to one thing: how well they strike their irons.</p>

<p>The good news? Iron play is learnable. Understanding a few key principles and practicing the right drills can transform your ball striking in weeks, not years.</p>

<h2 id="why-irons-are-different-from-your-driver">Why Irons Are Different From Your Driver</h2>

<p>Before diving into tips, you need to understand a fundamental truth: <strong>iron technique is the opposite of driver technique.</strong></p>

<p>With a driver, you sweep the ball off a tee on a slightly ascending arc. The ball is forward in your stance, teed up, and you want to hit up on it for maximum launch and distance.</p>

<p>With irons, everything changes:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>You hit down to make the ball go up</strong></li>
  <li><strong>The ball sits on the ground (or barely teed)</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Contact happens before the low point of your swing</strong></li>
  <li><strong>The divot comes after the ball, not before</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>This is counterintuitive. Your brain says “the ball is on the ground, so I need to help it up.” That instinct is wrong. Trust the loft on the clubface. Your job is to compress the ball into the turf and let physics do the rest.</p>

<p>For a complete breakdown of driver-specific technique, see our <a href="/2026/01/29/golf-driver-tips/">driver tips guide</a>.</p>

<h2 id="ball-position-for-every-iron">Ball Position for Every Iron</h2>

<p>Ball position determines whether you hit the ball first or the ground first. Get this wrong and nothing else matters.</p>

<p>Here is the general framework:</p>

<h3 id="long-irons-3-5-iron">Long Irons (3-5 Iron)</h3>

<p>Position the ball about one to two inches forward of center, roughly in line with the logo on your shirt or the inside of your front armpit.</p>

<p>Long irons require a shallower angle of attack than short irons. This slightly forward position lets you compress the ball while catching it cleanly. Move it too far back and you will struggle to get these clubs airborne.</p>

<h3 id="mid-irons-6-7-iron">Mid Irons (6-7 Iron)</h3>

<p>Your mid irons belong about one inch forward of center. Think of a spot between your sternum and your shirt logo.</p>

<p>This position promotes the ball-first contact that creates that satisfying divot after the ball. You are hitting down through the shot, compressing the ball for maximum control.</p>

<h3 id="short-irons-8-9-iron">Short Irons (8-9 Iron)</h3>

<p>Short irons should be positioned at or very near the center of your stance. This promotes a steeper angle of attack and better compression.</p>

<h3 id="wedges-pw-gw-sw-lw">Wedges (PW, GW, SW, LW)</h3>

<p>Wedges can be played at center or even slightly back of center for more control. The steeper angle creates the backspin that stops shots on greens.</p>

<p>For specialty wedge shots around the green, you might move the ball slightly back for lower trajectories or forward for higher, softer landings.</p>

<p>For a complete reference on ball position for every club, check out our <a href="/2026/01/30/golf-ball-position-guide/">ball position guide</a>.</p>

<h2 id="setup-adjustments-for-iron-play">Setup Adjustments for Iron Play</h2>

<p>Your setup with irons differs from your driver in several key ways.</p>

<h3 id="stance-width">Stance Width</h3>

<p>Narrow your stance compared to your driver. For mid irons, your feet should be roughly hip-width apart or slightly wider. For wedges, they can be even closer together.</p>

<p>A narrower stance allows better rotation through the ball. You do not need the stability of a wide stance because iron swings are shorter and more controlled than driver swings.</p>

<h3 id="weight-distribution">Weight Distribution</h3>

<p>At address, your weight should be roughly 50/50 or slightly favoring your lead foot (55% lead, 45% trail). With shorter irons and wedges, you can favor the lead side even more (60/40) to promote a descending strike.</p>

<p>This is different from driver setup, where weight is more evenly distributed or slightly favoring the trail side.</p>

<h3 id="posture-and-ball-distance">Posture and Ball Distance</h3>

<p>Stand slightly closer to the ball with irons than with your driver. The clubs are shorter, so you naturally stand closer. Bend from the hips, keep your back relatively straight, and let your arms hang naturally.</p>

<p>A good check: at address, a line dropped from your shoulders should fall just past your toes.</p>

<p>For more on proper setup fundamentals, see our <a href="/2026/01/17/golf-setup-stance/">setup and stance guide</a>.</p>

<h3 id="shaft-lean-at-address">Shaft Lean at Address</h3>

<p>With irons, your hands should be slightly ahead of the ball at address. This forward shaft lean is subtle, but it presets the impact position you want to achieve.</p>

<p>Do not overdo it. Your hands should be roughly above your front thigh, creating a slight lean toward the target.</p>

<h2 id="the-secret-to-pure-iron-shots-hit-down">The Secret to Pure Iron Shots: Hit Down</h2>

<p>Here is the most important iron tip you will ever learn: <strong>you must hit down on the ball to make it go up.</strong></p>

<p>This sounds backward, but it is how golf physics works. The club’s loft turns your downward energy into upward ball flight. When you try to help the ball up by scooping or flipping, you actually deloft the club and produce weak, inconsistent contact.</p>

<h3 id="what-hitting-down-looks-like">What Hitting Down Looks Like</h3>

<p>At impact with a well-struck iron:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Hands are ahead of the ball</strong> (shaft leaning toward target)</li>
  <li><strong>Weight is on the lead foot</strong> (approximately 80%)</li>
  <li><strong>The clubhead has not yet reached its low point</strong></li>
  <li><strong>The ball compresses against the turf</strong></li>
  <li><strong>The divot starts after where the ball was</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>The low point of your swing should be 2-4 inches ahead of the ball. You strike the ball first, then the club continues down and takes a divot in front of where the ball was sitting.</p>

<p>For a deep dive into what proper impact looks like, read our <a href="/2026/01/26/golf-impact-position/">impact position guide</a>.</p>

<h2 id="what-your-divots-tell-you">What Your Divots Tell You</h2>

<p>Your divots are free feedback. Learn to read them and you can diagnose problems without any technology.</p>

<h3 id="divot-location">Divot Location</h3>

<p><strong>Divot starts after the ball</strong>: Correct contact. You hit ball first, then turf.</p>

<p><strong>Divot starts behind the ball (or no divot at all)</strong>: Fat or thin contact. Your low point is in the wrong place.</p>

<h3 id="divot-direction">Divot Direction</h3>

<p><strong>Pointing left of target (right-handed golfer)</strong>: Outside-in swing path. Expect pulls, slices, and weak contact.</p>

<p><strong>Pointing right of target</strong>: Inside-out swing path. Expect pushes, draws, and hooks.</p>

<p><strong>Pointing at target</strong>: Square path. This is the goal for most shots.</p>

<h3 id="divot-depth">Divot Depth</h3>

<p><strong>Deep divots</strong>: Steep angle of attack. Common causes include an over-the-top move, poor weight shift, or ball position too far back.</p>

<p><strong>Shallow or no divot</strong>: Could indicate good compression with solid ball flight, or thin contact if shots are low and weak. Look at your ball flight to interpret.</p>

<p>For a complete breakdown, see our <a href="/2026/01/14/golf-divot-pattern/">divot pattern guide</a>.</p>

<h2 id="common-iron-mistakes-and-how-to-fix-them">Common Iron Mistakes (And How to Fix Them)</h2>

<h3 id="mistake-1-casting-early-release">Mistake 1: Casting (Early Release)</h3>

<p>Casting is when you release your wrist angles too early in the downswing, throwing the clubhead at the ball instead of letting it lag behind your hands.</p>

<p><strong>What it looks like</strong>: The clubhead reaches the ball before your hands do. You lose the shaft lean that creates compression.</p>

<p><strong>The result</strong>: Fat shots, weak contact, inconsistent distances, and ballooning ball flight.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Focus on maintaining your wrist hinge longer into the downswing. Feel like your hands get to the ball before the clubhead. The pump drill (described below) helps groove this feeling.</p>

<h3 id="mistake-2-scooping-flipping-at-impact">Mistake 2: Scooping (Flipping at Impact)</h3>

<p>Scooping happens when you try to help the ball into the air by flipping your wrists through impact, adding loft instead of compressing the ball.</p>

<p><strong>What it looks like</strong>: At impact, your hands are behind the ball instead of ahead of it. The shaft leans away from the target.</p>

<p><strong>The result</strong>: Thin shots, fat shots, high weak balls, and inconsistent distances.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Trust that the club’s loft will get the ball airborne. Practice pressing your hands forward through impact. The towel drill (below) prevents scooping by forcing ball-first contact.</p>

<h3 id="mistake-3-hitting-up-on-the-ball">Mistake 3: Hitting Up on the Ball</h3>

<p>This is the instinctive mistake. You see the ball on the ground and try to lift it. Your body rises through impact, pulling the club up with it.</p>

<p><strong>What it looks like</strong>: Your body straightens through impact (early extension). Your head moves up and away from the ball.</p>

<p><strong>The result</strong>: Thin shots, topped shots, inconsistent low point, alternating fat and thin contact.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: Stay in your posture through impact. Feel like you are hitting the ball into the ground, not up into the air. Keep your chest covering the ball longer.</p>

<h3 id="mistake-4-weight-staying-back">Mistake 4: Weight Staying Back</h3>

<p>If your weight does not transfer to your front foot during the downswing, your low point stays behind the ball.</p>

<p><strong>What it looks like</strong>: At impact, your weight is still on your back foot or evenly distributed. Your head may be well behind the ball.</p>

<p><strong>The result</strong>: Fat shots, thin shots (from overcorrecting), inconsistent contact.</p>

<p><strong>The fix</strong>: At impact, 80% of your weight should be on your front foot. Practice the step drill (below) to force proper weight transfer.</p>

<p>For more on fixing fat and thin shots, see our detailed guide on <a href="/2026/01/23/stop-fat-thin-shots/">stopping fat and thin shots</a>.</p>

<h2 id="adjusting-for-different-irons">Adjusting for Different Irons</h2>

<p>Not all irons are created equal. Here is how to adjust your approach based on the club in your hands.</p>

<h3 id="long-irons-3-5-iron-1">Long Irons (3-5 Iron)</h3>

<p>Long irons are the hardest clubs to hit because they have less loft and longer shafts. Here is how to improve your contact:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Ball position more forward</strong> (but not as forward as driver)</li>
  <li><strong>Shallower swing</strong> than with short irons</li>
  <li><strong>Sweep more, dig less</strong> (divots will be shallower)</li>
  <li><strong>Trust the club</strong> and swing smoothly; do not try to help it up</li>
  <li><strong>Consider hybrids</strong> if you consistently struggle</li>
</ul>

<p>Many amateurs play their long irons too far back, creating too steep an angle and chunky contact.</p>

<h3 id="mid-irons-6-7-iron-1">Mid Irons (6-7 Iron)</h3>

<p>These are the workhorses of your bag. The technique here is the standard iron swing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ball just forward of center</li>
  <li>Moderate divot depth</li>
  <li>Full weight transfer</li>
  <li>Committed downward strike</li>
</ul>

<p>If you can hit your 7-iron well, you can hit any iron well. This is your benchmark club.</p>

<h3 id="short-irons-8-9-iron-1">Short Irons (8-9 Iron)</h3>

<p>Short irons should be your most consistent clubs. The shorter shaft and higher loft make them easier to control.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ball at center of stance</li>
  <li>Steeper angle of attack</li>
  <li>Deeper divots than long irons</li>
  <li>Focus on precision over power</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="wedges">Wedges</h3>

<p>Wedges require the steepest angle of attack and the most aggressive downward strike.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ball at center or slightly back</li>
  <li>Narrowest stance</li>
  <li>Weight can favor lead side more at setup</li>
  <li>Prioritize spin and control over distance</li>
  <li>Practice partial swings for distance control</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="four-drills-to-transform-your-iron-play">Four Drills to Transform Your Iron Play</h2>

<h3 id="drill-1-the-towel-drill-fix-casting-and-scooping">Drill 1: The Towel Drill (Fix Casting and Scooping)</h3>

<p>Place a folded towel 3-4 inches behind the ball. Make swings without hitting the towel.</p>

<p>The only way to avoid the towel is to strike ball first with forward shaft lean. If you cast or scoop, you will hit the towel before the ball.</p>

<p><strong>Progression</strong>: Start with half swings, then three-quarter swings, then full swings at reduced speed. Once you can consistently miss the towel, remove it and maintain the same feeling.</p>

<h3 id="drill-2-the-line-drill-control-your-low-point">Drill 2: The Line Drill (Control Your Low Point)</h3>

<p>Draw a line in the dirt or use a stripe on the range mat. Make swings trying to brush the ground just after the line.</p>

<p>No ball at first. Just focus on where your club contacts the turf. Your divot should start on or after the line, never before.</p>

<p>Once you can consistently bottom out past the line, add a ball positioned just behind the line. Now you have a target for ball-first contact.</p>

<h3 id="drill-3-the-step-drill-force-weight-transfer">Drill 3: The Step Drill (Force Weight Transfer)</h3>

<p>Set up normally. As you start your downswing, step your front foot forward 3-4 inches, then hit the ball.</p>

<p>This forces weight transfer to your front side because you literally cannot hit the ball without moving forward first. It is an exaggerated feeling that creates lasting change.</p>

<p><strong>Variation</strong>: Practice with your back foot already pulled back and resting on its toe. This presets the weight forward and makes fat shots nearly impossible.</p>

<h3 id="drill-4-the-pump-drill-groove-the-downswing-sequence">Drill 4: The Pump Drill (Groove the Downswing Sequence)</h3>

<p>Make your backswing, then start down but stop when your hands reach hip height. Pause. Return to the top. Repeat 2-3 times.</p>

<p>On the final repetition, continue through and hit the ball.</p>

<p>This drill grooves the correct first move down (hips leading, hands dropping) without the distraction of hitting at the ball. It also helps maintain lag and prevents casting.</p>

<p>For more on the proper downswing sequence, see our <a href="/2026/01/25/golf-downswing-sequence/">downswing guide</a>.</p>

<h2 id="putting-it-all-together">Putting It All Together</h2>

<p>Here is your iron play checklist:</p>

<p><strong>At Setup:</strong></p>
<ul class="task-list">
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Ball position appropriate for the club (forward for long irons, center for wedges)</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Stance slightly narrower than driver</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Weight 50/50 or slightly favoring lead side</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Hands slightly ahead of the ball</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Posture athletic, bent from hips</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>During the Swing:</strong></p>
<ul class="task-list">
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Complete weight transfer to front foot</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Hips lead the downswing</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Hands stay ahead of clubhead into impact</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Hit down through the ball</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Stay in your posture; do not stand up</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>After Impact:</strong></p>
<ul class="task-list">
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Divot starts after where the ball was</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Divot points at target (or close to it)</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Weight finishes on front foot</li>
  <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" />Balanced finish position</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="use-video-to-verify-your-progress">Use Video to Verify Your Progress</h2>

<p>You cannot see your own impact position. It happens too fast. But video analysis can freeze that critical moment and show you exactly what is happening.</p>

<p>Look for:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Hand position relative to the ball at impact</li>
  <li>Whether your low point is ahead of the ball</li>
  <li>Weight distribution at impact</li>
  <li>Divot location and direction</li>
  <li>Whether you are staying in posture or standing up</li>
</ul>

<p>Many golfers think they are hitting down when video shows otherwise. Objective feedback beats guesswork every time.</p>

<h2 id="strike-your-irons-like-a-pro">Strike Your Irons Like a Pro</h2>

<p>Want to see your iron swing in action? Swing Analyzer shows you your impact position, shaft lean, and low point frame by frame. Upload a video and get AI feedback on your ball striking in 90 seconds. Find out exactly why you are hitting it fat, thin, or pure, plus get a fun grade and handicap guess.</p>

<p>Your irons are your scoring clubs. Make them count.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Great iron play comes from trusting the fundamentals: hit down, ball first, weight forward. Master these principles and you will compress the ball like never before.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Swing Analyzer Team</name></author><category term="instruction" /><category term="ball-striking" /><category term="iron play" /><category term="ball striking" /><category term="golf tips" /><category term="irons" /><category term="compression" /><category term="divots" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Master your irons with these proven tips. Learn ball position, proper setup, common mistakes to avoid, and drills to compress the ball like a pro.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-iron-tips.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fulcria-labs.github.io/assets/images/golf-iron-tips.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>